<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some helpes to stirre up to Christian duties Wherein is explained the nature of the dnty [sic] of stirring vp ourselves. Instances are given in the most necessary Christian duties. Some questions about this subiect are profitably resolved. By Henry Whitfeld B D. preacher of Gods word, at Ockley in Surrey</title>
            <title>Some helpes to stir up to Christian duties.</title>
            <author>Whitfield, Henry, 1597-1660?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1634</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 198 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 127 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A15114</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 25410</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101726</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837532</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837532</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1858</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A15114)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1858)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1400:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some helpes to stirre up to Christian duties Wherein is explained the nature of the dnty [sic] of stirring vp ourselves. Instances are given in the most necessary Christian duties. Some questions about this subiect are profitably resolved. By Henry Whitfeld B D. preacher of Gods word, at Ockley in Surrey</title>
                  <title>Some helpes to stir up to Christian duties.</title>
                  <author>Whitfield, Henry, 1597-1660?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, corrected and enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[20], 228 [i.e. 230] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Bartlet, and are to be sold at his shop, at the Gilt Cup in Cheape-side,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1634.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>An edition of: Whitfield, Henry.  Some helpes to stir up to Christian duties.</note>
                  <note>Last word of title reads "enlarged".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1858:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1858:1"/>
            <p>SOME HELPES <hi>TO</hi> STIRRE UP TO CHRISTIAN DVTIES.</p>
            <p>Wherein is explained the Nature of the Dnty of <hi>ſtirring vp our ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Inſtances are given in the moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Chriſtian Duties.</p>
            <p>Some Queſtions about this Subiect are profitab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y reſolved.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Henry Whitfeld,</hi> B D. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reacher of Gods Word, at <hi>Ockley</hi> in <hi>Surrey</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The ſecond Edition, Corrected and</hi> enlarged.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hn Bartlet,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop, at the Gilt-Cup in <hi>Cheape-ſide.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>34.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:1858:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1858:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE, ROBERT GREVIL, Lord <hi>BROOKE,</hi> of <hi>Beauchamp-Court,</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Grace.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">C</seg>Onſidering how hard a thing it is, by reaſon of that fraile and corrupted nature we carry about with us, to profit by
<pb facs="tcp:1858:3"/> praiſe; and finding moreover,<note n="a" place="margin">Vt quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis eſt lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de digniſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus ita mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nime lib en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuas au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dite ſolet laudes. <hi>Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chol.</hi>
               </note> that the more deſerving and worthy any are of it, the leſſe deſirous they are to heare it; Iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Lordſhip to be of the ſame minde, I reſolved not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine you with matter of that nature; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther indeed dare J give<note n="b" place="margin">Iob 32.22</note> flattering Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, fearing the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret reproofe and
<pb facs="tcp:1858:3"/> ſtroke of God in my owne Conſcience. I have adventured to addreſſe this Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, partly for the ſhrowding and ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring this little Booke under your Honours name and protection, which I humbly crave; and partly becauſe J deemed your Lordſhip a fit patron of it, the Lord having added
<pb facs="tcp:1858:4"/> this to al his other fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vors, as to give you a hart ſtirred up in du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Service &amp; Honour, which is the ſubiect of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe; I conceived alſo ſome hopes that you might ſee ſomething in it, whereby you might be farther pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked and ſtirred up in the earneſt Love, and open profeſsion of the Truth wherof you
<pb facs="tcp:1858:4"/> have given abundant Teſtimony before many witneſſes, which this Treatiſe cals for, and gives ſome light unto. Bleſsed be the Divine Maieſty, who (notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the great ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of that Sentence in Holy Writ,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.20.</note> 
               <hi>That not many wiſe men after the Fleſh; not many mighty, not many Noble are called</hi>) hath, in your freſh and
<pb facs="tcp:1858:5"/> floriſhing times, amidſt the confluences of many worldly bleſſings and contentments, looked upon you, and made choice of you for himſelf to doe him ſervice, and hath taught you to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the world as it is; when he hath paſſed by ſo many of high birth, and of great ranke and quality, who are migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily enthralled, and lye proſtrate, adoring the
<pb facs="tcp:1858:5"/> ſeeming felicities of this preſent world. What re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains then but that you advance forward, and doe ſtill more Nobly &amp; worthily, improving thoſe ſingular endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments beſtowed on you to the beſt advantage of the giver of them. Thus ſhall the Lord ſtill goe on to performe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 2.30.</note> 
               <hi>That ſuch as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour him he will ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> The truth and
<pb facs="tcp:1858:6"/> comfort of which I doubt not but your Lordſhip hath already found and felt, the greater &amp; more excellent part of which remaines to be fulfilled to you when your earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly honour is layed in the duſt, and your ſoule ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced to that hoped for perfection. For the full accompliſhment whereof hee ſhall ever pray, who reſts</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips to be commanded in all Chriſtian Service,</hi> Henry Whitfeld.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1858:6"/>
            <head>The Epistle to the <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Christian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>Vr ſpirituall life being the moſt choyce and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous treaſure that we carry about us in theſe our earthen veſſels, in the lively ſenſe and operations of which conſiſts the very life of our lives, and the the height of our comfort and ſolace here below: How needfull is it that we conſider of all meanes, and wayes, by which this life may be preſerved, and inlarged, that we may have it in more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. And this we ſhould the rather doe, both in regard of
<pb facs="tcp:1858:7"/> thoſe inward annoyances, which flowing from our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt nature, doe cauſe many faintings, and decayings even in the beſt, as alſo in regard of thoſe evils, which comming from without, and breaking in upon this life, do wondrouſly waſte, weaken, and hinder the operations of it. Now as it fares with our naturall life, that ſtirring and exerciſe proves ſpecially helpefull for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of it; ſo that which makes our ſpirituall life more lively, and fils it with ſtronger ſpirits, and activeneſſe, is the exerciſing of the ſeverall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and faculties of it, the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gifts and graces of it, in all thoſe acts and wayes in which it is to put forth it ſelfe. The ſerious thought of which hath cauſed me (Chriſtian Reader) to make this Eſlay, and to come to thy helpe in what I might in this ſhort diſcourſe following:
<pb facs="tcp:1858:7"/> The matter I know is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and of generall uſe for all Gods people, though the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of handling of it will not be found ſo notionall, accurate, or judicious; yet finding none, as I could call to minde, that had travelled in this Subject, I thought my weakneſſes in this kinde might bee ſheltered un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my deſire of a more gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall good.</p>
            <p>I conſidered alſo I had many of my Chriſtian friends, and neereſt kindred farre removed from mee, who being part of my care, I was willing to put ſomewhat into their hands, which might, not onely bee as a pledge of my love to them, and ſome direction for them, but might alſo (by Gods bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing) have ſomewhat in it to quicken them up in their Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian courſe. I ſaw my glaſſe running out apace, and I knew it would bee a griefe of heart
<pb facs="tcp:1858:8"/> unto me, if either they or I had beene called for hence, before I had left with them ſome proofe of my care and love, which I conceived might beſt be effected this way.</p>
            <p>I viewed alſo the way, and courſe of many profeſſours of Religion, even of ſuch as are counted of the forwarder ſort; where I found much ſloth, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warmeneſſe, and backſliding. I thought if I could throw but a ſparke into the heart of any ſuch, who did know what a fire it might kindle: In many alſo (though well minded) there is plainly to be ſeene a lowneſſe, and flatneſſe of ſpirit, together with a contentedneſſe to goe an eaſie and ordinary pace in their Duties and performances: Now if I could but a little heighten the affections, deſires and endevours of ſuch, and cauſe them ſomewhat to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance and put forward, it
<pb facs="tcp:1858:8"/> would bee abundant recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for what-ever paines I could beſtow in this kind.</p>
            <p>I found alſo I had a dull and ſluggiſh heart of my owne, which by this meanes might haply be quickned up, and that thus ſetting rules, and lawes to my ſelfe, what I had written might be of further uſe for me for the time to come.</p>
            <p>Some fruit alſo, and accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance I found amongſt ſuch, where I preached over theſe Notes, in a ſhorter manner. All which layed together have now prevailed with me to doe that which I never intended to do, <hi>viz.</hi> to give way to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of them, and bringing them into a more open light. What-ever I have done, I offer it unto thy view, and ſubmit it to thy loving cenſure; hoping, that if thou gaine ought by what is written, thou wilt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him at the Throne of
<pb facs="tcp:1858:9"/> grace, whoſe ayme and end was meerly thy profiting. And thus, beſeeching the Lord in mercy to guide us with the Spirit of wiſdome and meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in writing and reading, that we may be able to give up a comfortable account of both in the great day of our recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings; I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> H. WHITFELD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1858:9"/>
            <head>The Contents of the ſeverall Chapters of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> THe Coherence and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Text. <hi>page. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> That Gods people doe charge themſelves with more ſecret ſins than any elſe doe. <hi>p. 13</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> How Gods children ſhould ſeeke unto God in evill times, when he gives tokens of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. <hi>p. 29</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> That the worke of a Chriſtian in reſpect of a ſpirituall eſtate, lyes moſt with himſelfe. <hi>p. 39</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> About this Chriſtian duty of ſtirring up our ſelves, and what
<pb facs="tcp:1858:10"/> it is to ſtirre up ones ſelfe in Chriſtian duties. <hi>p. 66</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> What the maine duties are about which we are to ſtirre up our ſelves. <hi>p. 73</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Section 1.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in the most weighty buſineſſe of our owne and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers ſalvation. <hi>p. 74</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 2.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves againſt our owne ſins. <hi>p. 89</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 3.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves againſt the ſinnes of others. <hi>p. 94</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 4.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves when we come to God in prayer for our ſelves. <hi>p. 99</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 5.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves when we come to pray for others. <hi>p. 102</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 6.</hi> Of ſtirring up our
<pb facs="tcp:1858:10"/> ſelves in prayſing God. <hi>p. 106</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 7.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in ſtanding for God and his honour. <hi>p. 109</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 8.</hi> About ſtirring up our ſelves in the reading &amp; hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Gods holy Word. <hi>p. 116</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 9.</hi> About ſtirring up our ſelves in Meditation. <hi>p. 122</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 10.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in ſanctifying the Lords day. <hi>p. 129</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 11.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in our partaking of the Sacraments. <hi>p. 131</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 12.</hi> How to ſtirre up our ſelves in laying hold on the Promiſes. <hi>p. 138</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 13.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in the duties of love and mercy. <hi>p. 151</hi>
                     </item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1858:11"/>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 14.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in regard of our Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>stian race. <hi>p. 154</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Sect. 15.</hi> How we are to ſtirre up our ſelves when our last end approacheth. <hi>p. 157</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> Shewing the grounds of this Duty of ſtirring up our ſelves. <hi>p. 164</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> Where the doctrin of ſtirring up our ſelves is applyed in the ſeverall uſes of it. <hi>p. 170</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> Shewing ſome Motives unto this duty of ſtirring up our ſelves. <hi>p. 204</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> Shewing ſome Rules and Meanes by which we might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to this ſtirringneſſe of heart. <hi>p. 217</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1858:11"/>
            <head>SOME HELPES TO STIR UP TO CHRISTIAN DVTIES.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ISA. 64.7.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And there is none that calleth upon thy Name, that ſtirreth up himſelfe to take hold on thee.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> The Coherence and Reſolution of the Text.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe words are part of a Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion part of a prayer, which the Prophet
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:1858:12"/> poures out unto God, upon occaſion of the ſad, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolate eſtate of the Church of God, to be cauſed by the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> which the Prophet foreſeeing in ſpirit, ſpeaketh of it as preſent. For it may appeare by the ſad expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation which the Prophet maketh with God in the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter end of the former Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that God had given up his people to <hi>the errour of their wales,</hi> and <hi>to the hardneſſe of their hearts:</hi> and, which much aggravated their mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery and calamity, God had taken away the meanes of their Reformation (which were the holy Ordinances of his Worſhip) by giving up his Sanctuary to be trodden downe of the Adverſaries;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1858:12"/> ſo that now they were over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed both with Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, and outward Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments together; inward de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions, and outward deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations both of Church and Common-wealth, <hi>Chap.</hi> 63. <hi>verſ.</hi> 17, 18.</p>
               <p>Now looke as when the Ciſternes are dry, and the Conduit-pipes are broken, men are wont to have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the Fountaine for ſupply of living water: ſo in this dry and dead eſtate of the Church, when the wayes of Gods people were foule, and their hearts worſe, and themſelves left deſtitute of all meanes of redreſſe and ſuccour, the Prophet loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth up to God in heaven: and becauſe the ſuccour they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1858:13"/> ſtood in need of, was a work of great power and glory, hee burſteth forth into a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hement and earneſt prayer, calling unto God to come out of heaven, to worke their Salvation and Redemption for them with his mighty and glorious power: <hi>Oh</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>that thou wouldeſt rent the heavens and come downe, that the mountaines might flow downe at thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence:</hi> meaning, that God would ſuddenly and ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhew forth the might of his glorious power in their behalfe; that ſo thoſe moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of difficulties, which hindered their deliverance and reſtitution, might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, or at leaſtwiſe melt, and give way to them, <hi>v.</hi> 1.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:1858:13"/>
               <p>Now this prayer of the Prophet (which taketh up this whole Chapter) conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth of three principall parts:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of a Petition, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. to the 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of a Confeſſion, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Of a Deprecation, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. to the 12. which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Chapter.</p>
               <p>In the Petition (which is the firſt part of the prayer) the Prophet earneſtly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voketh God to manifeſt his glorious power, and fierce wrath againſt their adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries: his glorious power is expreſſed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>That hee renting the heavens, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming downe, the mountaines might flow at his preſence.</hi> His
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1858:14"/> fierce wrath, <hi>verſ.</hi> 2. <hi>That as when melting fire burneth, the fire cauſeth the water to boyle;</hi> So the fire of Gods wrath, burning againſt their adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, as droſſe (though mountaines of droſſe) yet they might boyle, and melt, and waſt away.</p>
               <p>This petition the Prophet worketh upon God with an holy and ſpirituall wraſtling by a threefold argument:</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the glory of Gods great Name; that ſo hee might <hi>make his Name knowne to his Adverſaries, and the Nations might tremble at his preſence, Verſ.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the ancient, ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, and glorious power, which God ſhewed forth in their deliverance out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:1858:14"/> and in the promulgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Law, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>When thou didd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>terrible things which we looked not for, thou cammeſt down, the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines flowed at thy preſence.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. From the unſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; unconceiveable riches of the grace of the Goſpell, which from the <hi>beginning God hath prepared for his people that wait for him, verſ</hi> 4. and ſo the Apoſtle expoundeth the place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.9.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of this Chapter, and of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets prayer, is the Confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion that he maketh, and that of two things:</p>
               <p n="1">1. Of Gods readineſſe to ſhew mercy, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Of their unprepared<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to receive mercy, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1858:15"/> of any deſert of their owne, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5, 6, 7.</p>
               <p>Gods readineſſe to ſhew mercy, is expreſſed in the beginning of the fifth verſe, <hi>Thou meeteſt him that reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth and worketh righteouſneſſe, thoſe that remember thee in thy wayes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their unpreparedneſſe to receive mercy, is expreſſed, firſt, generally; and then particularly.</p>
               <p>Generally, in regard of their ſinnes, and of Gods juſt diſpleaſure againſt them for their ſinnes, in the next words; which yet he quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth with hope of ſalvation, by the continuance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of Gods wayes of grace and mercy to his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1858:15"/> he, <hi>thou art wroth, for we have ſinned,</hi> (and ſo are unworthy and unfit for mercy) <hi>yet in thoſe,</hi> to wit, in thoſe wayes of thine (wayes of grace and mercy, prepared in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell from the beginning of the world) <hi>in thoſe is continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> and conſtancy, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding our undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingneſſe) <hi>and wee ſhall bee ſaved.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>More particularly, their unpreparedneſſe for mercy is expreſſed, <hi>verſ.</hi> 7. in a double reſpect:</p>
               <p n="1">1. In reſpect of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſſe and filthineſſe, not only of their corrupt nature, but even of their beſt acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and duties, <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. <hi>But we are all</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>as an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing, and all our righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1858:16"/> are as filthy ragges, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In reſpect of their ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual dulneſſe and ſloth to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe ſuch graces and duties as might turne away Gods wrath, and remove their ſins and miſery: <hi>Verſ.</hi> 7. <hi>There is none that calleth upon thy Name, that ſtirreth up himſelfe to take hold on thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the third part of this prayer and Chapter (which is the Deprecation) the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet earneſtly prayeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſoreneſſe or great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Gods wrath, and the everlaſting remembrance of their iniquities, <hi>verſ.</hi> 9. and this requeſt hee preſſeth upon God by two Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments:</p>
               <p n="1">1. By the mutuall inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1858:16"/> they have in God, and God in them; <hi>Thou art our Father, our Potter;</hi> wee <hi>thy children,</hi> and <hi>as clay in thy hand,</hi> verſ. 8. <hi>Wee thy people,</hi> verſ. 9. <hi>thou therefore our King.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. By the deſolate and forlorne condition of Gods owne Cities; yea, of his, and their <hi>holy, and beautiful houſe, verſ.</hi> 10.11. Which injuries and indignities the Prophet demands with a patheticall queſtion, how he can endure to looke at, and refraine and hold his hands from redreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>verſ.</hi> 11.</p>
               <p>To returne to the words of the Text, they be (as you ſee) a Confeſſion or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint of the latter of thoſe evils, which made them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1858:17"/> and unprepared to receive mercy; to wit, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of their Spirituall dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and untowardneſſe to the exerciſe of ſuch Graces and Duties, as might turne away Gods wrath, and their ſinnes together. Wherein obſerve,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The generality of this Spirituall dulneſſe; it is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pidemical, common to them all, none free from it; <hi>there is none</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that calleth, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The Duties neglected, which were two:</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Calling upon Gods Name</hi> (though in a moſt needfull time.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Taking hold of God;</hi> by which is meant, either by faith laying hold of his Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1858:17"/> or elſe figuratively, as it were, holding God, and ſtaying him that hee depart not from them, keeping him with them, as <hi>Saul</hi> would have kept <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.27. And this latter hee am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plifieth by their neglect of the very endevour after it: <hi>None ſtirreth up himſelfe to take hold of thee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> That Gods people doe charge themſelves with more ſecret ſinnes than any elſe doe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANd there is none that cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth upon thy Name.]</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee come to lay forth
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1858:18"/> the maine thing intended, it will not bee amiſſe to take a ſhort view of ſome paſſages in the Text as they lye in our way.</p>
               <p>And firſt in generall, from the nature of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint; if wee looke to the matter of it, we ſhall finde it to be not ſo much in regard of their preſent preſſures, and evils which lay upon them; neither for groſſer ſinnes, which were more open and obvious to the eyes of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but for more inward and ſecret corruptions, and failings, ſuch as the world takes no notice of, or will hardly bee brought to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge they are ſinnes at all; or if ſo, yet not worthy the troubling themſelves for
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1858:18"/> them; as <hi>not to have ſtriven with the Lord in their prayers, to ſtay the iudgment threatned; and not to ſtirre up themſelves to hold the Lord, that he depart not from them.</hi> Hence wee may obſerve,
<q>Gods Children, in the times of confeſsion of their ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, are wont to charge themſelves with more cloſe and ſecret evils and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Their complaints are ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with bitter bewailings of more inconſpicuous and indiſcernable evils, of wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe more ſpirituall, not to be perceived by a carnall eye, and therfore not lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a carnall heart.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:1858:19"/>
               <p>To give ſome inſtances: As,</p>
               <p>For their<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 51.5 Iſay 64.6</note> birth-ſinne, that corrupted maſſe they brought into the world, which ſteames like a dung-hill, and ſends up ſtench and unſavorineſſe into the whole man; hindering in all duty, and putting forward unto all evill.</p>
               <p>They complaine of thoſe remainders of Atheiſme, of their wicked and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thoughts, of ſtrong objections riſing up in their mindes againſt cleare and evident truths; as againſt the very Being of God, the worke of our Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by our Saviour Chriſt, the truth of Gods Word, and many ſuch like. So alſo they lament their<note n="a" place="margin">Pſa. 31.22. Pſa. 116.11</note> Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leefe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1858:19"/>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 12.7 He that tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God of the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine God applyed to heale and prevent the exalting of himſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, ſecretly confeſſeth the privy proneneſſe of his owne heart to ſelfe-exal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</note> privy Pride,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſa. 51.10. Praying for a right Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he confcſſeth his owne ſpirit not right nor ſtreight, but crooked and deceitfull.</note> ſecret hypocriſie,<note n="d" place="margin">Iſay 6.5. Nehem. 13.22. His great zeale for reformation, yet needeth great mercy to ſpare it from exact examination.</note> and the evill which cleaves to their beſt works, their ſelfe-love, ſelfe-ſeeking, and<note n="e" place="margin">Pſalm. 30.6.</note> ſelf-confidence, their great<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 106.6, 7. Nehem. 9.35.</note> unprofitableneſſe under all thoſe meanes, and mercies offered, their<note n="g" place="margin">Iſay 63.17.</note> hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, and that great<note n="h" place="margin">Prov. 30, 2, 3. I feele ſuch ignorance of God and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l his wayes, ſo many yeares towards mee, ſuch folly which keepeth mee from taking any thing to heart which reſpecteth God, or concerneth my ſelfe; ſuch uncircumciſion of heart, which maketh mee that I cannot be holy, poore, and abiect, though conſci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ous of innumerable Motives, paſt, preſent, imminent, whieh might move mee thereunto. Laſtly, I feele ſuch a ſelfe-ſufficiency as will not let mee perceive what need I have of my God to be with mee for quickning, ſtrengthening, comforting, directing, proſpering of mee in my courſe. <hi>Baines,</hi> Letter 19.</note> blindeneſſe and ignorance which they finde in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; it much grieves them many times for their
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1858:20"/> unruly<note n="i" place="margin">Pſa. 73.3.22</note> paſſions, and their<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 45.9.</note> ſtrivings with God, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patiencies under his hand; their ſecurity, lukewarme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and not<note n="k" place="margin">Cant. 1.6.</note> keeping their Watch; their<note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 32.15 Nehe. 9.28</note> abuſing law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full things; their<note n="m" place="margin">Hoſ. 8.12.</note> unthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe for Spirituall mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies; their<note n="n" place="margin">Ezech. 9.4 Iſa. 42.19, 20</note> not mourning for the ſinnes of the land, and of the places where they live; nor taking to heart ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall judgements; their<note n="o" place="margin">Ier. 9.3.</note> fearefulneſſe and aptneſſe to be diſcouraged, and give out in good buſineſſes, and Gods cauſes; their too much<note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.9</note> indulgency and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring themſelves, and thoſe that are neare unto them in their faults and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings; ſo<note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 78.37 38, 40,</note> their often breach of promiſe, and Covenant
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1858:20"/> with God;<note n="r" place="margin">Iſa. 64.7.</note> their ſleight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and perfunctorineſſe in the ſervice of God; much irreverence, &amp;c.<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 26.40 43.</note> their dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, heavineſſe, wearineſſe, indevotion, together with their diſtractions, and diſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations of heart in holy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; their<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 8.18</note> forgetfulneſſe,<note n="u" place="margin">Hoſ. 6.4.</note> inconſtancy, and<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 43.5.</note> uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable walking in their Chriſtian courſe. Theſe and ſuch like doe make them ſigh in ſecret, ſhake their heads, and wring their hands, and cry out with many a bitter cry when none eye ſees them, or eare heares them.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>
                  </label> The grounds and Reaſons of this, amongſt others, are ſuch as theſe:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This proceeds from that divine, and ſpirituall light,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1858:21"/> they have received into their minds (being hence de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominated<note n="a" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 55,</note> children of light, and called<note n="b" place="margin">Eph. 5.8</note> light in the Lord by which they diſcerne theſe cloſe and hidden corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, being now by this light made, as it were, tranſparent unto themſelves. For looke as it is with luminous and lightſome Bodies, as a Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, Chriſtall, Glaſſe, or the like; when the light of Sunne-beames ſhine upon them, it cauſeth a tranſparen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in them, ſo that the foule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe within is as viſible as the fouleneſſe without; ſo it is here. The word uſed by the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. will ſerve ſomewhat to explaine this: Hee tels the Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, that in ſimplicity, and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1858:21"/> godly ſincerity hee had had his Converſation in the world, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Vid. Bez ad loc,</note> 
                  <hi>i. e.</hi> in all candour, and perſpicui y of ſpirit and heart; as in the ſight of God, which might plainely bee ſeene even through and through. Now as the good, ſo is the evill in Gods Children tranſparent; as the ſpots which appeare in the face of the Moone, ſo that by the help of this light they are able to paſſe a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon themſelves, and their more ſecret evils.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The Conſcience being renewed, and having this light ſhining into it, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed into it from the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, hath alſo this quality of Tenderneſſe, by which it quickly ſmites and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1858:22"/> bleeds for knowne, though cloſe ſinnes, and ſo affecteth the heart with ſorrow for them.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> They being Spirituall, they can conceive and judge of ſpirituall things; As of God, whom they ſerve, to be a Spirit; of his Law and worſhip, by, and in which they ſerve him, to bee Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall. Now as the Law is, ſo is the tranſgreſſion; where there is no Law, that is, no ſpiritual apprehenſion of the Law, there men cannot con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne themſelves for ſecret and cloſe ſinnes: <hi>Paul</hi> is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live when without the Law,<note place="margin">Rom. 7.9.</note> and hee is without the Law whilſt carnall; but <hi>Paul</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing become ſpirituall, the Law alſo is become ſpiritual
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:1858:22"/> unto him, <hi>verſ.</hi> 14. So that ſpirituall and ſecret ſinnes ſo apprehended he could then judge of, which before hee could not.</p>
               <p>Yet we are to know,<note place="margin">Caution.</note> that this worke of bewayling ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret evils, is not found in all Gods children alike, ſince their Conſciences are not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually inlightned, and made tender; neither are they all alike mortified, or watchful; nor have they the Spirit of judging and diſcerning alike; neither are all ſo eaſily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced alike; but this is found in all, ſo farre as their light goes, there will be ſmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for guiltineſſe in theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> Hence wee have a broad difference betweene thoſe
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1858:23"/> confeſſions which are found in the truly penitent and humbled ſoule, and thoſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary large formes taken up by carnall men, either by cuſtome, or extorted from them by their naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in ſome painefull and helliſh pangs of it: As <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh</hi> in extremity cryed out, <hi>I have ſinned this time,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exod. 9.27</note> 
                  <hi>the Lord is righteous, and I and my people are wicked.</hi> So <hi>Saul</hi> being convinced of his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſt and unnaturall dealing towards <hi>David,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Sam. 26.21 1 Sam. 24.17</note> ſaid, <hi>Returne my ſonne David, I will no more doe thee harme. I have played the foole, and have erred excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</hi> Thus was it with <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> in the groſſe and open caſe of betraying his Maſter;<note place="margin">Matth, 27.4</note> 
                  <hi>I have ſinned in betraying in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1858:23"/> blood.</hi> When the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience hath but Natures light, it muſt be a great print that a man can read in this kinde, taking knowledge on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of more groſſe and ſtaring evils, and that moſt an end againſt the ſecond Table: but the regenerate goe far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as I have ſaid, confeſſing and lamenting their inward &amp; ſecret corruptions, which the hypocrite ſwallowes up, as not worth the naming.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Hence it may appeare that the world is extremely miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and hath much to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer for thoſe hard and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell ſpeeches which are eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where uttered againſt ſuch; that they are proud, and deſpiſers of others; that they are Hypocrites, and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1858:24"/> Diſſemblers, &amp;c. whereas they appeare in their owne eyes doubly vile, and twice as ſinfull: For in others their open and outward ſins onely are apparent, but in themſelves they behold both their open and inward ſinnes, which muſt needs breake downe all high thoughts of themſelves, and cauſe them to prefer others above themſelves.</p>
               <p>Neither can they bee ſo charged with Hypocriſie, ſince the fouleneſſe of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide of the platter is ſeene, and bemoaned, and waſhed with teares by them, as well as the outſide: They are more troubled for praying, than thou for not praying; for hearing, than thou for
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1858:24"/> not hearing, &amp;c. This being ſeldome found in the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of any hypocrite to lay ſuch things as theſe to heart, abounding ſo much in ſelfe-love, and ſelfe-deceit, and being ſecretly willing to reſt in his preſent condition, and to make his bed as eaſie, and to lye as ſoft as hee can, and ſo to reſt with as little diſturbance as may bee; hee will not ſearch for matter to trouble himſelfe, but keeps up himſelfe in as good an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme with himſelfe and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as poſſibly hee may; nothing troubling him more than to know, or be knowne what ſecret guile and rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenneſſe there is in his ſpirit; and therefore loth, not only to heare others ſpeake, and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1858:25"/> complaine of it to him, but to heare himſelfe ſpeak and complaine of it to God, is an heavy, irkſome, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing worke; only Gods childe, as hee is willing to know the worſt of himſelfe, ſo will he confeſſe the worſt of himſelfe in the eares of the Lord;<note place="margin">Iuſtus fave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ſibi ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcit rigorem iudicis circa ſe non novit infl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ctore. <hi>Amb. Apol. cap. 9.</hi>
                  </note> none thinking or ſpeaking ſo bad of them, as they doe of themſelves; and none laying ſo much to their charge, as they doe to their owne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> This alſo may bee for a comfort, and ſtay to the hearts of the godly in the time of trouble, and houre of darkeneſſe, when Satan ſhall rake in their hearts for matter to increaſe their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſtreſſe, and ſhall caſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1858:25"/> their ſecret failings in their faces, yet then when the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can beare witneſſe, and the diſtreſſed ſoule can truly ſay in Gods preſence, The Lord knowes theſe evils have not wanted complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning againſt,<note place="margin">In quantum non pep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> ceris tibi in tantum tibi Deus par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et <hi>Tertul. de poenit.</hi>
                  </note> ſecret though they be, I have often ſpread them before the Lord, as my ſores and ſorrowes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> How Gods Children ſhould ſeek unto God in evill times, when hee gives tokens of his diſpleaſure.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THere is none that calleth upon thy Name.]</hi> This is the firſt thing they charge
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1858:26"/> themſelves withall; not that they were altogether praier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, as the Heathen, or prophane; but it grieved them that this their ſervice had not beene according to the Law of prayer; they had not intended their inward affections to apprehend the Lord, to keepe him with them in their affliction, they were ſluggiſh, and did not ſeeke to ſtay Gods wrath before the judgment came. Hence we may obſerve, <q>In evill times, when the Lord gives tokens of his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, then not to call upon him with intention of ſpirit, increaſeth ſinne and wrath.</q>
               </p>
               <p>This appeares, whether it
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1858:26"/> be an evill time with a mans ſelfe, or with a Land and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: <hi>The Hypocrites in heart</hi> (ſaith <hi>Elihu</hi> in <hi>Iob) put to wrath, or heape it up,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob 36.13</note> 
                  <hi>becauſe they cry not when God bindeth them;</hi> having wilfull and rooted ſtubbornneſſe in them, habituall contempt of God, without all reverence of his word, or Rod; that even in adverſity they will not ſubmit themſelves to God, but obfirme and har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den themſelves under the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils. Of this alſo the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy</hi> complains,<note place="margin">Ier. 5.3</note> 
                  <hi>Thou haſt ſtricken them, but they have not grieved.</hi> The people ſtriving and ſtomacking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God, they intreat not his mercy and favour, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their curſe is augmented
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:1858:27"/> more and more,<note place="margin">Verſ. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>verſ.</hi> 6. This the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> affirmed of the people of his time; <hi>The people turneth not to him that ſmiteth them,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſay 9.13</note> 
                  <hi>neither doe they ſeeke the Lord of hoaſts; therefore the Lord will cut off from Iſrael, head and taile, branch and ruſh in one day.</hi> So in <hi>Zephany,</hi> the Lord threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens the neglecters of his worſhip, not only Idolaters, and thoſe that mingled their Religion with ſuperſtitions: but <hi>thoſe that have not ſought the Lord,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zeph. 1.6</note> 
                  <hi>nor enquired for him: i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> e.</hi> not ſought him by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and intreated his helpe in ſuch a declining and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt time.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> What cauſe then have men to feare Gods hand go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out againſt them? whoſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:1858:27"/> courſe and practiſe, if it were ſearched with a candle, it would bee found that they had never opened their mouthes, nor lifted up one petition this way, ſeeing what deſolations have beene wrought in forraine parts, what tokens of his diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure amongſt our ſelves in the land wee live in; nay, when the Lord hath knock'd at their owne dores, brought it home to them, and the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry markes and ſignes of his anger have been upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, their wives, or chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, yet then to have the heart ſo ſinke and fall, and to be ſo over-growne with ſenſeleſneſſe, as not to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to commend the caſe of themſelves, or theirs, to the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1858:28"/> Lord; this ſhewes the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſme of the heart; for in what degree a man is praier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, in that degree hee is godleſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> How may it humble Gods owne children? How may it goare our very hearts, and make them bleed, that wee have beene ſo wretchedly wanting both to God, our owne ſoules, the good of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and the good land in which God hath planted us? How juſtly may we take up the confeſſion of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Daniel,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Dan. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.13, 14</note> 
                  <hi>All this evill is come upon us, yet made wee not our prayer before the Lord our God. Therefore hath the Lord watched upon the evill, and brought it upon us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How may they call and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1858:28"/> cry to us out of the <hi>Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, Bohemia,</hi> and other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, &amp; ſay, Some of you have ſeene, and moſt have heard of the grievous evils that have befallen us;<note place="margin">Lam. 1.12</note> 
                  <hi>Behold and ſee if there were ever ſorrow like unto our ſorrow,</hi> to have the glorious Goſpell of Chriſt taken from us, the Arke diſplaced, and <hi>Dagon</hi> ſet in his roome; our Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters baniſhed, and our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple betrayed unto Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianiſme; our Country laid waſt and deſolate, m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ny a Family driven from houſe and home, not knowing where to lay their heads; many of us ſeldome going to bed with dry eyes, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the many preſſures, ſtraights, and neceſſities of
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1858:29"/> our ſelves and ours. O then why were your prayers and teares wanting to helpe to extinguiſh the flame of Gods wrath broken out againſt us? May not many amongſt our ſelves of this land cry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us, when Gods hand hath been upon them by the <hi>Pestilence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 91.6.</note> 
                  <hi>which walked in the ſtreets at noone-day;</hi> by Famine, and other miſeries, yet our prayers have not bin with the Lord with intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. O we put not forth our ſelves as wee ought to have done, by ſtrong cryes in the behalfe of the diſtreſſes of our bretheen: What may we thinke is juſtly owing us to this day for our great neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lects herein? the Lord grant it be not laid to our charge.</p>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:1858:29"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Let us hence be exhorted to be more frequent, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent in this ſervice in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe of our ſelves, Gods Church, and people: To make amends in time to come, plying the Throne of grace with all earneſtneſſe, whileſt we ſee the judgment hanging in the threatning, or already executed upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, leſt this ſtare thee in the face another day, and thy conſcience upbraid thee when the day of thy calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty hath overtaken thee, or thou art enwrapt in the common judgement, and ſay unto thee, Remember, the time was when thou ſaweſt Gods judgements on the Land, the Church, &amp;c. and thou heldeſt thy peace, and
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:1858:30"/> didſt not helpe by thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as thou oughteſt to have done; ſee now how heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and ſhiftleſſe thou art, and it is juſt with God it ſhould bee ſo; O this will adde to the bitterneſſe of the croſſe, and ſtrike the ſtings of it deeper into thy Spirit. On the other ſide, if thou haſt diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>harged thy conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence this way, if the worſt fal,<note place="margin">Zeph. 2.2</note> yet either <hi>thou ſhalt be hid in the day of Gods wrath,</hi> or <hi>with Noah,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 14.14</note> 
                  <hi>Daniel, and Iob, thou ſhalt deliver thine owne ſoule;</hi> or thou ſhalt be migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily aſſiſted, and furniſhed with faith and patience to undergoe the preſent afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and thy prayer ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne into thy owne boſome like <hi>Noah</hi> his Dove into the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1858:30"/> Arke, with an Olive branch of peace in its mouth; and God, who hath beene a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy heart and waies, will looke to it, that thou ſhalt not loſe thy reward.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IIII.</hi> That the worke of a Chriſtian, in reſpect of his ſpirituall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state, lyes moſt with himſelfe.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>OR that ſtirreth up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.]</hi> This is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond part of their complaint they had beene ſluggiſh and drowſie, they had not beene dealing with themſelves, nor labouring with their owne hearts for quicknance
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1858:31"/> and ſtirringneſſe; they did not ſtirre up [themſelves.] Hence obſerve,
<q>The buſineſſe of a Chriſtian, in regard of his ſpirituall eſtate, ſhould lye much with himſelfe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>A Chriſtian hath of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers the greateſt buſineſſe, and this lies in many places; in heaven, in the Church, in the Family, in the Cloſet, &amp;c. and though God ſet him his worke, and give abilities to doe it, yet in regard of the tranſacting and perfecting this worke, it hath ſpeciall, and primary relation to a mans ſelfe, and ſpecially to that part of a mans ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lfe which wee call the Inner
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:1858:31"/> man, as his minde, and thoughts, wil, and affections, and Conſcience; God being a Spirit, with whom our principal buſineſſe lieth; and the ſervice being Spirituall, in which we are to addreſſe our ſelves unto him; its the ordering and managing of our ſpirits that lyeth upon us, as the chiefeſt of our im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment. See it in ſome In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances:</p>
               <p>Firſt, in the great buſineſſe of Repentance, and turning to God: we ſhall finde this in Scripture to be called<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 24.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>A comming to a mans ſelfe:</hi> To make this farther to appeare let us take the whole order and courſe of this worke.</p>
               <p>It pleaſeth the Lord, at ſome time of a mans life, ſuch
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1858:32"/> an one whom he purpoſeth to ſave, by the Miniſtery of the Word, together with the helpe of the Spirit, to meet in his way to Hell, where there is diſcovered unto him the vileneſſe and horrible<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his ſinnes, and the fearefull eſtate the ſinner is caſt into by reaſon of theſe: The conſcience is now a wakened, the books are ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, hee ſees ſinne clearely, and is convinced of them, ſo that he cannot ſhift, hee cannot deny them; his thoughts alſo beginne to be troubled, and to beat one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another with unſavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry perturbations; finding all is not well, he goes alone by himſelfe, begins to ſearch, reads his ſinnes as in a ſtory;
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:1858:32"/> his conſcience tels him, <hi>I am ſent unto thee with heavy ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings;</hi> and one meſſenger followes another to tell him of his loſt and condemned eſtate:<note n="b" place="margin">Dan. 5.27</note> 
                  <hi>To thee be it ſpoken, thou art weighed in the bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and found too light;</hi> theſe be thy ſinnes, and theſe will be thy ſorrowes. Being thus perplexed, he begins to caſt about, and to conſider what way hee were beſt to take to extricate, and unwind himſelfe out of theſe Mazes and Labyrinths of ſinne and miſery: He lookes upward, and ſees heaven ſhut againſt him; he lookes downward, and findes hell opened for him; he lookes round about him, and ſees no helpe in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny creature, men, or Angels;
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:1858:33"/> he lookes into himſelfe, and findes innumerable ſinnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſing him about, which ſtare upon him, and having every one, as it were, a chain in their hands, they are bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him hand and foot, to caſt him into utter darkneſſe. Being caſt into theſe great ſtreights, ſuch thoughts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to riſe in his minde, (God being mercifull to him;) Is there not mercy with the moſt High? Will hee caſt off any poore ſinner that comes unto him? And therfore reſolves and ſaith, Sure<note n="c" place="margin">Luk, 15.18</note> 
                  <hi>I will ariſe and goe, and I will ſay</hi> to the Lord, <hi>I have ſinned againſt heaven, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee;</hi> who can tell but the Lord may ſhew mercy to as great a ſinner as I am?
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1858:33"/> He comes therfore, and caſts himſelfe downe before the Throne of grace, and ſaith,<note n="d" place="margin">Iob 7.20.</note> 
                  <hi>What ſhall I ſay unto thee, O thou preſerver of men?</hi> I have no arguments to plead, no excuſes to make, no reaſons to defend my ſelfe withall; my ſighes are my beſt Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, and my teares are my beſt arguments: O that thou wouldeſt pitty! O that thou wouldſt ſpare! O that thou wouldſt have mercy upon a poore worme, a wretched and forlorne ſinner! Thus all alone he humbleth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hee<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 32.5</note> confeſſeth his ſinnes, and ſpreadeth them before the Lord,<note n="f" place="margin">Eze. 20.43</note> 
                  <hi>loathing himſelfe in his owne ſight;</hi>
                  <note n="g" place="margin">Luk. 15.21</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſeth himſelfe;<note n="h" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.31.</note> 
                  <hi>iudgeth himſelfe worthy to be deſtroied:</hi>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:1858:34"/> He now beholds<note n="i" place="margin">Iohn 3.14</note> Chriſt lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up to him (as the brazen Serpent in the wilderneſſe) which he ſees with his own eyes, embraceth with the armes of his owne faith, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes him to himſelfe for his owne everlaſting com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort. And thus his ſinnes pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue him to the Sacrifice of Chriſt, to this City of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge, giving him no reſt, till Chriſt ſpeake peace to his ſoule: and all this is done by a man with himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, as it is thus in regard of Initiall Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, ſo is it in regard of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed Repentance; when a man falls into ſinne after cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to get up againe, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover, the buſineſſe lies with a mans<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 4.4</note> ſelfe. Thus we<note n="l" place="margin">1 Kin. 8.47</note> read
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1858:34"/> in 1 <hi>King.</hi> 8.47. <hi>When Gods people are carryed captive into their Enemies Land,</hi> the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is, that yet <hi>if they ſhall bethinke themſelves, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and make ſupplications, &amp;c. then God would heare them:</hi> He ſpeakes it of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed Repentance, of them who are already Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; and this hee cals <hi>a be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking themſelves,</hi> or a brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging backe a mans heart, a going downe into a mans ſelfe; and anſwerable to this is the other expreſſion in the ſame Chapter, <hi>ver.</hi> 36. <hi>When they ſhall know every man</hi> (that is, particularly) <hi>the ſoare and plague of his owne heart.</hi> Thus alſo, <hi>Levit.</hi> 16.29. the children of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael were <hi>to afflict their ſoules</hi>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:1858:35"/> and to make bitter to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the remembrance of former ſinnes, they were<note n="m" place="margin">Eze. 16.62 63, &amp; 36.31</note> voluntarily to caſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into heavineſſe: ſo <hi>Peter</hi>
                  <note n="n" place="margin">Luk. 22.32</note> 
                  <hi>went out</hi> by himſelfe <hi>and wept bitterly.</hi> As it is with a man in times of taking Phyſicke to recover health, hee betakes himſelfe to his chamber, takes the potion preſcribed, and is contented to be pained, and made ſicke: So in this Repentance, which is Spirituall Phyſicke, the worke lyes by ones ſelfe: as it is in <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.11. <hi>They went apart, the Land ſhall mourne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Family apart, and their wives apart.</hi> Thus wee ſee it in the buſineſſe of Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>It is the ſame alſo in the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1858:35"/> work of Mortification. How doth it lye with a mans ſelfe, as the ſeverall phraſes in Scripture, pointing to this, import; when a man is to<note n="o" place="margin">Grandis virtutis eſt tecum pug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare quoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die etinclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum hoſtem centum o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culis obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare. <hi>Hieron. ad Fur.</hi>
                  </note> fall out with himſelfe, and to have great<note n="p" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.11</note> 
                  <hi>indignation a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt himſelfe; to</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Gal. 5.24</note> 
                  <hi>crucifie his luſts,</hi> and corruptions; to<note n="r" place="margin">Mat. 18.8</note> cut off, as it were, the parts and members of ones owne body, as <hi>to pull out our eyes,</hi> to <hi>cut off foot or hand;</hi> to<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.27</note> 
                  <hi>keepe under the body;</hi> to<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 8.34</note> 
                  <hi>deny a mans ſelfe;</hi> all which ſeeme terrible and bloody words to corrupt nature, and carnal reaſon; yet about this muſt a Chriſtian be exerciſed, and that by himſelfe.</p>
               <p>Againe, when feares and doubts riſe in that great and weighty matter whether we
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1858:36"/> have any part or right in Chriſt or no? this queſtion muſt be reſolved by<note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 13.5</note> 
                  <hi>proving and trying a mans owne ſelfe,</hi> by a private ſearch and ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny, which muſt be made in our owne boſomes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, ſee it briefly in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of ſome particular du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, we ſhall find the worke ſtill to lye with ones ſelfe; as in</p>
               <p n="1">1 Hearing and Reading the holy Word of God: <hi>Heare it</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iob 5.27</note> (ſaith <hi>Eliphaz to Iob) and know it for thy good,</hi> or for thy ſelfe, as it is in the Margent. When we apply things to our ſelves, as the Diſciples upon that ſpeech of Chriſt unto them, <hi>One of you ſhall betray me: they</hi>
                  <note n="x" place="margin">Mat. 27.22</note> 
                  <hi>as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked every one, Master is it I?</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:1858:36"/> To doe as the Bee, which brings home the honey ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to her owne Hive, there layes it up to nouriſh her, and to feed upon it as need requires. A man muſt ſo looke into the Word that he<note n="y" place="margin">Iam. 1.23</note> 
                  <hi>may ſee his owne face in it as in a glaſſe;</hi> and ſo helping himſelfe to reforme what is amiſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In ſinging of Pſalmes the<note n="z" place="margin">Epheſ. 5.19</note> Apoſtles counſell is, that <hi>wee ſhould ſpeake to our ſelves, ſinging and making melody in our hearts to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. In preparing to come to the Sacrament of the Lords Supper, wee are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horted<note n="a" place="margin">1 Cor. 11 28</note> 
                  <hi>to examine our ſelves</hi> before we come.</p>
               <p n="4">4. When croſſes and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1858:37"/> breake in upon us, and God layes his hand on us, we are <hi>to</hi>
                  <note n="b" place="margin">Lam. 3.28</note> 
                  <hi>ſit alone by our ſelves,</hi> pondering and conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the grounds and cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of them; ſo quieting our ſelves, that wee may beare them with patience.<note n="c" place="margin">Jer. 15.17</note> 
                  <hi>I ſate alone becauſe of thy hand</hi> (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h the Prophet <hi>Ieremy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> This private, particular, and punctuall dealing with a mans ſelfe, wil much work out hypocriſie, and make all our performances to be with much more ſincerity; which doth moſt appeare in our perſonal performances, ſince every man is trulieſt that, that hee is in private, and by himſelfe, in his ſecret reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redneſſe, and when ſeparated from all ſpectators and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1858:37"/> For here indeed lyes the ſtreight and pinch of our Chriſtian worke:</p>
               <p>To be wreſtling with God in prayer; To bee dealing hand to hand againſt our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved corruptions, and to keepe a conſtant and cloſe fight againſt them; To be much in ſelfe-examination; To be gaging our own harts, and digging into our ſelves to finde the roots of our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full diſtempers, to rake in the puddle and ſincke that is in our owne boſomes, and to ſmell the ſtench and unſavo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rineſſe of it, to bee humbled by it: Theſe, theſe are thoſe private and painfull workes which muſt be done, if ever thou meane to make ſure worke for thy ſoule, and
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:1858:38"/> without which all thy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion is but a ſelfe-decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
               <p>In our more publike and open performances alſo this hath place: So to tend to our hearts, and ſpirits, that they bee preſerved in their ſtrength and intention in the duty, beyond what will ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie men, as in Hearing, Receiving, Praying with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, &amp;c. all which may be done with eaſe by the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man; but doe thou ſay to thy ſelfe, this charge muſt I alwayes lay upon my ſelfe in all duties that are of pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Obſervation, to doe them from my ſelfe, not from others; that is, to ſet upon them from ſuch a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor of ſpirit as would carry
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1858:38"/> mee to ſuch performances, even from my ſelfe, if there were none to behold me.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Secondly, there can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be any ſaving worke up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the heart without this, and that by reaſon of the <hi>deepe</hi>
                  <note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 17.9</note> 
                  <hi>deceitfulneſſe of our hearts, and deſperate wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</hi> A man can lay no ſure foundation of his houſe, that diggeth not deepe beneath all quicke-ſands, and rotten ſoyle, ſo here.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> This ſerves for great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe of ſuch who have no ſuch kind of buſineſſe with themſelves, but are ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers in their owne boſomes, altogether ignorant what paſſeth in their owne hearts, whether they get or loſe, whether they draw nearer
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1858:39"/> to heaven or hell; of ſuch the Prophet complaines,<note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 8.6</note> 
                  <hi>None ſaith what have I done?</hi> They live abroad out of themſelves, looking and pry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing into others, but leave their owne hearts neglected and untill'd. Nay, they ſhunne, and decline this worke as a grievous taske. Oh, mee thinkes it is a folly and a madneſſe, that wants a name to expreſſe it, that Man, a reaſonable creature, endued with ſuch abilities, and ſo fitted every way for this worke, and it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a buſineſſe of that great conſequence, yet that hee ſhould make ſuch an eſcape from himſelfe, and live at ſuch a diſtance from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo farre out of his
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1858:39"/> owne call and reach! Oh what ſtudying is there in the world of ſundry ſorts of ſalutations, garbs, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements? What asking of each others health and wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare?<note n="g" place="margin">Nullum tibi anima tua propinquiorem nullum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t ces chariorem Si te amiſeris omnia in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rdis. <hi>Salv. lib 3. cont. Avarit. Of all priſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, uſe oft neſt to viſit thine owne ſoule.</hi> Greenham. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp;c Intende <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae oculum in tuum i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> examin ut noſca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne anpecus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at anima <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Baſil.</hi>
                  </note> yet never to aske his ſoule how it fareth; not ſo much as to bid it good mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, or good even; I meane, he paſſeth it by as a worth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and a neglected thing. What great deſire have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to viſit farre Countries, and to know the manners and cuſtomes of other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions farre or neere? What long Pilgrimages doe many make with many a weary ſtep? yet they will not take a ſhort journey downe into their owne hearts, nor know the behaviour and language
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:1858:40"/> of their owne ſoules and conſciences. The grounds of this extreame folly may be ſuch as theſe:</p>
               <p n="1">1. In many it proceeds from Ignorance, they know not what this duty meanes, or that there is any ſuch work reqvired of them, they know not how to behave themſelves in ſuch a buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In many it proceeds from ſlothfulneſſe, they will not be at the paines,<note n="h" place="margin">Eſt et he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> perverſitas hominum mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>itius, quam curati deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derare.</note> they chooſe rather to put things to the venture, ſpeed as it may: They ſay they keepe their Church, ſay their prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, come to the Sacrament, pay every one his owne, &amp;c. if this wil not ſerve the turn, but that there muſt be ſuch
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1858:40"/> adoe, then God helpe. They thinke ſuch as call for more, or doe more, are more buſie then needs, and that farre leſſe would ſerve the turne.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In many it proceeds from a ſtrange levity, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſedneſſe, flotingneſſe, and unſetledneſſe of Spirit; they cannot keep their mind ſteddy, nor ſerious in this worke, but are quickly tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned aſide to other things, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven a feather flying in the ayre will divert and take them off, and cauſe them to wander in vanity and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinencies.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In ſome it proceeds from a guilty fearefulneſſe; they will not bee too buſie this way, to pry into them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, fearing leſt they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1858:41"/> might ſee that which would make their hearts ake to ſee, by cauſing the remembrance of their former evill wayes to returne upon them: They think it would bring a damp on their worldly comforts, and marre their carnal mirth making them grow mellan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicke and mopiſh, and ſo expoſe them to the ſcorne of the world, or their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions, and carnall friends.</p>
               <p n="5">5. In ſome it is from worldlineſſe, and earthly-mindedneſſe; they will not afford ſo much time, being carried along with ſuch great intention and vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency of Spirit, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be at<note n="i" place="margin">As if a ſicke man ſhould ſay, I have no leiſure to be cured.</note> leiſure for this bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe. But canſt thou be at leiſure to eat, drinke, and
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1858:41"/> ſleepe? Canſt thou finde a time to looke upon thy Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, corne, and bagges? To laugh and be merry? nay, to lye, ſweare, drinke, &amp;c. Be thou aſſured, that ſo continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, God will not be at lei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to forgive thee thy ſins, or ſave thy ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> Try therefore what buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe hath beene diſpatched this way, with thy ſelfe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thy Spirituall eſtate; what peace procured, what occaſions of ſinne prevented, what corruptions maſtered, what watch kept, what rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>konings caſt up, what doubts cleared, what graces increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; what duties practiſed, what temptations reſiſted, what proviſion made for ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, what time thou haſt
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1858:42"/> ſpent by thy ſelfe about theſe things; be aſhamed for thy failings, and bleſſe God har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily for any time ſpent, or thoughts had, or progreſſe made about theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> Bee exhorted to ſet thy ſelfe to this worke, thy hand to this plough, ſtudy thy ſelfe, read thy ſelfe, reaſon much with thy ſelfe, and converſe frequently with thy ſelfe, conſult and adviſe with thy ſelfe about thy Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eſtate, be ever ready to returne into thy ſelfe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all occaſions, what ever befals thee; comforts or croſſes, mercies or miſeries. When fallen into any ſinne, traverſe quickly thoſe<note n="k" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Iam. 1.22.</note> 
                  <hi>falſe reaſonings</hi> of thy hart which drew thee into it. Say to thy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1858:42"/> ſelfe, how came this to paſſe? As <hi>Abſolon</hi> ſaid to <hi>Thamar,</hi> when ſhee came weeping with duſt upon her head,<note n="l" place="margin">2 Sam. 13.20</note> 
                  <hi>Hath Ammon bin with thee?</hi> So, Hath Satan beene with thee? Hath paſſion over-born thee? Hath Pride ſwelled thee? Have worldly cares choked thee, &amp;c. How came this about?</p>
               <p>To move us further to this duty, take theſe few helps:<note place="margin">Motives,</note>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. This, of all other acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of life, is the moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and tends moſt to the perfecting of the ſoule, which is the moſt excellent part; this perfects a man as hee is a Chriſtian: Other thoughts, and diſcourſes of thy Spirit may perfect thee as a man, a Scholler, a ſtateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:1858:43"/> and Common-wealths man, &amp;c. but this, as a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. This, being the moſt noble worke, and buſineſſe of the minde, puts a luſtre and beauty upon the ſoule. This is the ſpeciall part of wiſdome, and makes a man the wiſeſt man. All other thoughts and actions, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this returning into a mans ſelfe,<note n="m" place="margin">Ier. 17.11 Pro. 5.13, 14</note> leave a man at laſt in the midſt of folly and miſery.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. This makes the ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, and moſt ſetled Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, ſound in heart, in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and life; the neglect of this cauſeth ſo many er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours both in life and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. This keepes the ſoule and conſcience in a quiet and
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1858:43"/> peaceable ſtate, ſweet, cleane and comfortable, as often ſweeping keepes the houſe cleane; and often reckoning keepes long friends: This will make thee rejoyce in thy owne boſome, and the<note n="n" place="margin">Pro. 14.10</note> 
                  <hi>ſhranger</hi> from this worke <hi>ſhall not meddle with thy ioy:</hi> Otherwiſe the ſoule muſt needs be a loathſome place, and a cage for every un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane luſt and ſinfull vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:1858:44"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> About this Chriſtian Duty of ſtirring up our ſelues, and what it is to ſtirre up ones ſelfe in Chriſtian duties.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NOne that ſtirre up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.]</hi> This is the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Duty neglected, they did not ſtirre up themſelves to take hold on God, there was a neglect of the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour after it, which is here charged upon them: whence we have the Obſervation ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing plaine before us,
<q>It is our duty ſeriouſly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cite and ſtirre up our ſelves in all exerciſes of piety and Godlineſſe, with all inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:1858:44"/> of ſpirit, to our utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt.</q>
               </p>
               <p>For the further opening of the point, two things are to be explained:</p>
               <p n="1">1. What it is to ſtirre up ones ſelfe.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The things, about which, this duty is to bee converſant and exerciſed.</p>
               <p>For the firſt, to ſtirre vp a mans ſelfe, hath theſe two things in it:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The awaking of our ſelves, the ſhaking off that dulneſſe and drowſineſſe which cleaves to us. To this the Apoſtle hath reference, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.11.<note n="o" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Excitari. Expergiſci.</note> 
                  <hi>It is high time to awake out of ſleepe;</hi> he ſpeaks to ſuch as were already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted: Now this awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning is a freeing of our grace
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1858:45"/> from the oppreſſion it was under, by worldly cares, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall feares, or ſome ſinfull luſts, which cauſe a neglect of univerſall piety, and the workes of the light, and day of regeneration, unto which wee had our new Creation.</p>
               <p>The Beleevers, in their<note n="p" place="margin">Ferventior eſſe ſolet, qui rem primùm aggreditur.</note> firſt ſetting out, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly more earneſt and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent in following God cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them; the firſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions, and ſenſe of their bleſſed change affect more, which may bee gathered from the reproofe of the Church of <hi>Epheſus, in the loſſe of their first love,</hi> and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling her to <hi>remember from whence ſhe was fallen, to do her first works, Rev</hi> 2.4, 5. That ſeemes to be like it, <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.2.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1858:45"/> 
                  <hi>I remember for thy ſake the kindneſſe of thy youth,</hi> though that doth more principally declare the kindneſſe of God in taking that people to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before all other, as an argument of conviction, that for no cauſe, againſt all obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations of duty, they, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their firſt beginnings forſooke the Lord: As in proceſſe of time men grow colder, in their affections to him at leaſt, though they ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly forſake him not; the Prophet therefore cals upon them, and uſeth divers argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the verſes follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to put them upon the duties enjoyned them.</p>
               <p>Though Gods children are called out of the world, yet they have much of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1858:46"/> world in them ſtill, and therewith are miſerably en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thralled many times, ſo that we need awaking, and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up. In which reſpect it is that the Lord hath provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, as well goads to pricke forward the dull, as nailes to faſten them that are incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 12.11. See alſo for this, theſe following Scriptures, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.34. <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.24.</p>
               <p>The ſecond thing in the ſtirring up a mans ſelfe, is not onely the awaking up of our ſelves, but the ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worke that grace beſtowed, together with the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of our faculties in their ſanctification, to their utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt abilities. This may appeare by Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:1858:46"/> to <hi>Timothy, I put thee in remembrance that thou ſtirre up the gift of God that is in thee:</hi> as if he ſhould have ſaid, Conſidering thou haſt an unfained faith, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my great affection to thee, whereby I am care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of thee, I, with great confidence, put thee in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance that thou<note n="q" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>2 Tim. 1.6</hi> Sicut ignis indiget lignis, ita &amp; gratia alacritate, ut fervère perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuò poſſit. <hi>Chryſoſt. ad loc.</hi>
                  </note> quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up the holy fire that is in thee, and blow it up, uſe the grace thou haſt with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and ſtrength of Spirit. So againe the ſame<note n="r" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.1</note> Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Be ſtrong in the grace that is in Christ Ieſus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now as there is required great wiſdome and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection in ordering the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces given, and ſetting them in their right place and ſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1858:47"/> and ſo giving them their due worke and exerciſe; When, one ſaith, knowledge bee you ready to diſcerne what Gods will is; Faith, be you ready to beleeve what God promiſeth; Hope, be you ready to expect what is promiſed; Patience, be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to beare what the Lord inflicteth; Obedience be you ready to goe about what God commandeth: I ſay, as there is required this wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in ordering grace, ſo there is required great inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit in intending al inſtruments of motion, all faculties and powers of bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and ſoule, for the keeping theſe in their due height, that they ſlacke not, nor abate not of their former ſtrength
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1858:47"/> and vigour. Thus you ſee what it is to ſtirre up ones ſelfe, and wherein it ſtands.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> What the maine things are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which we are to ſtirre up our ſelves.</head>
               <p>SEcondly, we are to ſhew whereabout we are to ſtir up our ſelves, and what the duties are; to ſpeake, as the truth is, theſe are of large extent, and beare an equall latitude with all duties of Religion and godlineſſe; there being no duty, unto which this is not required, it being as the fire to kindle the Sacrifice, and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mark. 9.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9</note> 
                  <hi>as Salt</hi> to
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1858:48"/> ſeaſon it. I ſhall give in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in ſome particulars, ſuch as are of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which doe call for our utmoſt care and intention of ſpirit.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 1.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in the weighty buſineſse of our owne and others ſalvation.</head>
                  <p>FIrſt, concerning the moſt weighty buſineſſe of our Salvation, and our everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting eſtate, it is our duty that wee mightily ſtirre up our ſelves, and tend to the good of our precious ſoules above al things in the world beſide: about this, three things are ſpecially to bee
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1858:48"/> heeded by us:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. To take hold of all ſeaſons and opportunities for the furthering and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing this worke: For this end wee are to take a ſerious view of the times and places where wee live, to conſider what they afford and bring with them, what confluence and concurrence of meanes, more than at other times, or in other places. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle cals upon, and ſtirres up the <hi>Corinthians</hi> with this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument,<note n="t" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.2 Can. 2.10.13 Eſter 5 2</note> 
                     <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>now is the accepted time, now is the day of Salvation:</hi> that is, whilſt the light of the Goſpell ſhines, whilſt the Miniſters call, whilſt the Lord (like <hi>Ahaſueros</hi>) holds forth his golden Scepter, his
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1858:49"/> promiſes of mercy and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don to all ſuch as come to him, eſpecially when he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins to ſtirre the heart with touches and remorſes for ſinne, and deſires of mercy and pardon. The people that were ſtirred by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> how wonderfully eager were they in the purſuit of their Salvation?<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 11.12</note> 
                     <hi>From the dayes of Iohn Baptist untill now</hi> (ſaith our Saviour) <hi>the kingdome of heaven ſuffers vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, and the violent take it by force;</hi> that is,<note n="*" place="margin">Quidam ad omnia viae &amp; vita hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a non So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>mbulant ſed et c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rrunt, i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>o po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ius v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nt. <hi>Bern Serm. 3. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. ſ. Dom</hi>
                     </note> they would have no nay, they were ſet upon it; as if they ſhould have ſaid, What a time is this? What dayes be theſe of light and grace? Who ever periſh, wee will not:
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1858:49"/> Who ever goe to Hell, wee will not: As long as there was grace and mercy to bee had, as long as ſuch gracious offers were tendred unto them, they reſolved to refuſe no labour nor paines: reſt they cannot, have it they muſt, whatever it coſt them: Oh the ſtrong and reſtleſſe deſires! Oh the unwearied endevours of ſuch, whoſe hearts God hath truly tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with a care of their owne Salvation!</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. For our going forward in this bleſſed worke, and bringing of it to its height and full perfection, it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves: To this the<note n="x" place="margin">Phil. 2.12</note> Apoſtle ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horts, that <hi>we ſhould worke out our ſalvation with feare and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1858:50"/> trembling.</hi> As Salvation is a great worke, which ſhould take up our whole man, ſo it is ſtill to be wrought out, that if at any time wee were queſtioned what we were a doing, we might anſwer, we were working out our Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation with all our ſtrength; as the fountaine workes out the mudde, and as Phyſicke workes out the diſeaſe, ſo to be throwing out all that hinders, to bee ſtill<note n="y" place="margin">Sapiens qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diu vivit, tama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u addit.</note> adding to this worke, one grace to another, one duty to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; according to that of the<note n="z" place="margin">2 Pet 1.5 <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them hand in hand</note> Apoſtle, <hi>Giving all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, adde to your faith, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue; to vertue, knowledge, &amp;c.</hi> Be ſtil going onward to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as the<note n="a" place="margin">Heb. 6.1</note> Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth us; <hi>Therefore
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1858:50"/> leauing the principles of Chriſt, let us goe on to perfection.</hi> and againe,<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.1</note> 
                     <hi>Having theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, let us perfect holineſſe in the feare of God:</hi> ſo never ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our pace, or giving o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver our care, till wee had brought it to its full maturi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and this is to bee done <hi>with feare and trembling,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting that great ſeriouſneſſe of going about this worke, what a<note n="c" place="margin">Acts 7.32</note> feare ſhould fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our hearts, conſidering the great Majeſty of God, with whom wee have to deale; and our owne unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe and great inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency, as of our ſelves, to goe forth in ſo great and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty a worke: Neither is this feare, a blinde, or a ſervile feare, but ſuch as is accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:1858:51"/> 1. with Humility and lowlineſſe of minde, oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to high mindedneſſe, and ſelf-confidence; as <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.12. <hi>Be not high minded, but</hi>
                     <note n="d" place="margin">Timor vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uſios eſt. <hi>Hierony.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>feare.</hi> 2. With an awful and child-like reverence of God, oppoſed to wantonneſſe and carnall ſecurity; as <hi>Hebr.</hi> 12.28. <hi>Wherefore we receiving a kingdome which cannot bee moved, let us have grace, wherby we may ſerve God with reverence and godly feare.</hi> When we doe things in faith and obedience, and in great love to God and his holy Commandements, for his truth and goodneſſe ſake, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 3.5. Inſtance might be given in preaching the Word, by which Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are gathered to him; <hi>I was
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:1858:51"/> with you</hi> (ſaith the<note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.3</note> Apoſtle to the <hi>Corinthians) in weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in feare, and in much trembling.</hi> So in hearing, thus the<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 7.15</note> 
                     <hi>Corinthians received Titus with feare &amp; trembling.</hi> And the Lord<note n="g" place="margin">Iſay 66.5 Ezra 5.4</note> ſaith, <hi>he looks to ſuch;</hi> that is, with the eye of pitty and favor, <hi>that trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at his Word.</hi> So for prayer and other duties, which help forward this worke; and this wee muſt take for an everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting truth, that they alwaies ſpeed beſt, and have moſt aſſiſtance, and enlargement of heart in duties, that ſet to them in moſt Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and tremblingneſſe of Spirit.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To grow up to more and more full Aſſurance of our ſalvation, unto which
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1858:52"/> we are exhorted, <hi>Give all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence to make your calling and election ſure.</hi> Diligence here implieth, 1. Care of the heart, ſo rendred, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.11 2. Earneſt indevour, which hath in it ſpeed, inſtantneſſe, painefulneſſe, putting forth our beſt ſtrength thereunto, taking paines for God and our ſoules <hi>[to make our calling and election ſure]</hi> that is, that we be not diſappointed, or doubt or diſtruſt of it; the former is the aſſurance of the things in themſelves,<note n="i" place="margin">Certitudo obiecti.</note> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is in regard<note n="k" place="margin">Certitudo ſubiecti.</note> of us. This duty is to bee done, 1. by building our hope of both, not upon the Sand; that is, either upon<note n="l" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3</note> good nature, or<note n="m" place="margin">Matth. 3.9</note> Gods outward Covenant, or<note n="n" place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 7.21, 22, 23.</note> common graces, and du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1858:52"/> for theſe will deceive us, but upon the Rocke, which is Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7.24. and in him, upon his promiſe of Word &amp; Oath, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.18 2. By gathering certaine ſignes of our ſafe eſtate in him, as from our chuſing him for our God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.25. a ſure ſigne he<note n="o" place="margin">Ioh. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 19</note> firſt choſe us, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.19. ſo of our effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall calling, and the like. 3. Eſchewing ſuch evils as might darken, or dampe our Aſſurance, and breake the bones and ſtrength of it. 4. By adding grace to grace, and linking one to another, as you heard before. Thus you ſee what things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of us about this great worke and buſineſſe of our Salvation; and unto this wee
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:1858:53"/> ſhould the rather haſten with all our might, as in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other reſpects, ſo, in that priority in enjoying the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits of God in Chriſt, is a great prerogative; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſhould ſtir up them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves about it. To be firſt in Chriſt, hath ſpeciall pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileges; <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.7. <hi>Salute Andronicus and Iunia</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) who were in Chriſt before me:</hi> So is <hi>Epinetus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to be the <hi>firſt fruits of Achaia:</hi> The ſooner we get out of the world, which lyes in wickedneſſe, unto Chriſt, the ſafer we are, what ever befals us; and the more ſins and pollutions of the world ſhall we be freed from, and ſo the ſooner ſhall wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for the peace of our
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1858:53"/> conſciences, and the comfort of our lives.</p>
                  <p>Thus alſo are we to ſtirre up our ſelves, according to our places and callings,<note n="p" place="margin">Pecora fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tris tuo erran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia iubel ut reducas fratri tuo nedum ipſum ſibi. <hi>Tertul.</hi>
                     </note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the ſalvation of others, and to further the ſame with all earneſtneſſe of intention, by all the wayes and meanes we can, as they ſtand in rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto us. Thus <hi>Cornelius,</hi> taking the opportunity when <hi>Peter</hi> was to come to his houſe to Preach the Word unto him,<note n="q" place="margin">Acts 10.24</note> 
                     <hi>he gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his kinſmen and meere friends.</hi> So <hi>Andrew</hi> cals his brother <hi>Simon,</hi> and<note n="r" place="margin">Ioh. 1.40, 41</note> tels him <hi>We have found the Meſsiah,</hi> and ſo brought him to Ieſus. This being an infallible note of a good man, that hee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not tell how to goe to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1858:54"/> alone. This care, and deare affection ſhould ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially be found in Miniſters of Gods Word; how ſhould they ſtirre up themſelves when they come to perform this worke? Before them ſit the blinde, and ignorant; the proud, profane, and rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinner,<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.20.</note> 
                     <hi>held under the power of the Devill,</hi> and <hi>led captive by him, according to his will,</hi> who are making haſt, and fetch large ſtrides to the fiery Lake, which is but a little before them. What tender compaſſions ſhould they put on to bring home wandring ſinners, and<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 5.2</note> 
                     <hi>ſuch as are out of the way;</hi> that, if it were poſſible,<note n="u" place="margin">Acts 20.28</note> not one ſoule ſhould periſh, committed to their charge.</p>
                  <pb n="87" facs="tcp:1858:54"/>
                  <p>When the Lord is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call home a loſt ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and beginnes to lay a foundation of his bleſſed change in his ſoule, wee ſhould ſtirre up our ſelves by all ſignes of joy and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing. As it was when God put to his hand to lay the foundations of this glorious frame of the world, the Lord himſelfe tels us,<note n="*" place="margin">Job 38.7</note> that <hi>the morning ſtarres ſang together,</hi> and <hi>the Sonnes of God,</hi> that is,<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Ion. ad loc.</note> the Angels, <hi>ſhouted for ioy;</hi> much more when he begins<note n="x" place="margin">Amos 9.6</note> to build his <hi>ſtories</hi> of grace and mercy in the ſoule of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, it being a greater, and a harder worke to ſave one ſinner, than to make the world; becauſe in that work there was no reſiſtance, for
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1858:55"/> he did but<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 33.9 Gen. 1.3</note> 
                     <hi>ſpeake and it was done; he ſaid, Let there be light, and it was ſo;</hi> but in the ſoule of man there is great reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, who ſtands out as long as ever hee can, and God hath much adoe with us before hee can bring us home: therefore are wee to make it matter of great joy, even as it is to the holy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels themſelves, <hi>Who reioyce over one ſinner that repenteth, Luk.</hi> 15.10. Thus doth the Father of the prodigal child in the ſame Chapter,<note n="a" place="margin">Luk. 15. <hi>ult</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>It is meet</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that we ſhould make merry, and be glad; for this thy brother was dead, and is alive againe;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 10.21 Jeſus reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Spirit</note> 
                     <hi>he was loſt, and is found:</hi> and good cauſe have wee to rejoyce, one ſoule more being pulled out of the
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1858:55"/> Divels clawes, and king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; one more is added to the Church; one more, of a child of wrath, death, and hell, is made an heire of grace and ſalvation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 2.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our owne ſinnes.</head>
                  <p>THe ſecond thing, about which this duty of ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up our ſelves is to bee exerciſed, is in regard of ſinne, and Gods offence, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in regard of our ſelves, or others. 1. In regard of our ſelves, and our owne ſinnes.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. Firſt, in regard of our inbred and inherent corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:1858:56"/> wee are to ſtirre up our ſelves,<note n="b" place="margin">Incentiva vitiorum ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim in mente iugulabis, et parvulos Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilonis allides ad Petram. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
                     </note> in oppoſing and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting the inward motions, ſtirrings, and provocations of it, it is our duty to ſet our ſelves againſt them with all our might, to ſharpen our eyes againſt them, we ſhould labour to ſee Death, Hell, Wrath, and Gods curſe in the leaſt riſings and motions unto them; we ſhould looke upon Luſt, Pride, Malice, Revenge, thoughts of blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, &amp;c. as upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell himſelfe; we ſhould be no otherwiſe affected with the ſtirrings of theſe, then as if thou didſt feele a Toad or Serpent ſtirring &amp; crawling in thy boſome: O in what a caſe wouldſt thou then think thou wert? How wouldſt
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1858:56"/> thou ſhake thy ſelfe, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be at quiet till thou hadſt got forth that loathſome and venemous creature: So, and much more ſhouldſt thou<note n="c" place="margin">Dum in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitatione vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptas non re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>primitur, eti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am in actione dominaetur,</note> ſtrive and ſtruggle a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all motions and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations to ſinne. Say to thy ſelfe in ſuch a caſe, Oh theſe filthy luſts, whither wil they carry mee? How ſhall I bee able to looke God in the face, if I ſhould give way to it? And I muſt goe to him before I ſleepe,<note n="d" place="margin">Cavendum vulnus quod cum dolore Sanatur. <hi>Hieron. Ep. ad Sal.</hi>
                     </note> in what a caſe will my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence bee within this halfe houre? Begge hard of the Lord to keepe thee, and to give thee ſtrength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe ſinfull ſtirrings of thy corrupt nature. Thus have Gods Children with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:1858:57"/> ſucceſſe helped themſelves, when they have ſet them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves againſt the brood of the Devill, crying, as the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting <hi>Iſraelites</hi> againſt their Idols,<note n="e" place="margin">Iſay 30.22</note> 
                     <hi>Get thee hence,</hi> and ſo have preſerved their peace.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. When former ſinnes unrepented of come into thy remembrance, it is our duty to<note n="f" place="margin">Ionah 3.8</note> 
                     <hi>cry mightily</hi> againſt them, and to be in great bitterneſſe for them,<note n="g" place="margin">Zac. 12.10.</note> 
                     <hi>as one that is in bitterneſſe for his first-borne;</hi> even to cry out as a travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling woman, amidſt the pangs and throwes of guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tineſſe. Hence<note n="h" place="margin">2 Chr. 33.12</note> 
                     <hi>Manaſſeth</hi> is ſaid <hi>to humble himſelfe great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi> O when the <hi>fountaines of the</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 7.11.</note> 
                     <hi>great deepe are broken up,</hi> and the heart of the penitent ſinner beginnes to breake
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1858:57"/> and melt, there bee ſtrong grones and ſighes uttered, which pierce the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, and the voyce and cry of them is heard on high.</p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. When fallen into any ſinne, it is our duty to beſtir our ſelves<note n="k" place="margin">Licet lapſi ſint, non com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morentur in lapſu, nec in ipſis ſe ſepuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant ruinis ſuis ſed ilicò, ubi concidere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurgant, <hi>Salv. lib. 1. cont. Avarit.</hi>
                     </note> to get out of the mire, never to give thy ſelfe reſt in it, think thou lyeſt all the while amongſt ginnes, and ſnares, and Scorpions, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midſt quick-ſands, in which thou ſinkeſt deeper and dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per every moment thou ſo abideſt. Wee ſhould call to mind what <hi>Peter</hi> did in ſuch a caſe,<note n="l" place="margin">Luke 22.62</note> 
                     <hi>He went out</hi> preſently, <hi>and wept bitterly.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:1858:58"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 3.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst others ſinnes.</head>
                  <p>IN regard of others ſinnes it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves, and that in regard of the evill of doctrine, or judgement, or of life and converſation:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. For the evill of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, falſe and erroneous tenents, and poſitions, wee ſhould ſtirre up our ſelves<note n="m" place="margin">Iude 3.</note> 
                     <hi>to contend earnestly for the faith, once delivered to the Saints;</hi> not to loſe the leaſt dram of that precious do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine: we are not to looke for any more Goſpels, or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more truths to be penned
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1858:58"/> for us, therefore to looke well to theſe wee have. As they are penned and written for all Gods people, ſo all have intereſt in them; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Common Salvation,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iude 3.</note> al ſhould ſtand for it to their uttermoſt;<note n="n" place="margin">Mos iſte ſemper in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae viguit ut quó quiſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> foret religion fior eò promp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiùs novellis ad inventio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus contra ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t. <hi>Vincent. Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinenſ.</hi>
                     </note> ſo to ſtand a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that which is <hi>contrary to ſound Doctrine.</hi> Ah (deare Chriſtian) wee ſhould prize moſt dearely every truth of God, the leaſt of which is more precious<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 5.18</note> than <hi>heaven and earth,</hi> and a moſt ſweet and beautifull thing; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as every errour is loathſome and deformed,<note n="p" place="margin">Nova dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mata vetus Teſtamentum deos alienos appellare con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuevit. <hi>Id. Vinc.</hi>
                     </note> caſts a ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh on the moſt holy and pure nature of God, and tends to the ruine and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of all things. He that goes about to corrupt and
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1858:59"/> deboſh another in life and manners, by wicked coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, or example, is to bee ſhunned as a dangerous ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my; but he that goes about to corrupt and deboſh ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his judgement and underſtanding, which is the moſt precious and excellent part of man, and to ſpoyle him in his intellectuals, is to be accounted as a curſed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, and to be driven out from the ſociety of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde.<note n="q" place="margin">Revel. 2.2</note> The Church of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus</hi> was commended,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vid.</hi> Pareum ad loc.</note> 
                     <hi>that ſhee could not beare with them that were evill:</hi> that is, ſuch as were falſe Apoſtles, who carried about falſe doctrins, and corrupted others. How did Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſtand out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Elymas,</hi>
                     <note n="r" place="margin">Acts 13.9</note> 
                     <hi>who ſought to
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:1858:59"/> turne away the Deputy from the faith:</hi> How did he ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen his Spirit againſt him, ſaying, <hi>O full of all ſubtilty, and all miſchiefe, thou childe of the Divell, thou enemy of all righteouſneſſe, wilt thou not ceaſe to pervert the right waies of the Lord.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. In regard of the evill of life, and corruption of manners in others,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Ne ſitis neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentes in co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r gendis v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ad cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram veſtiam quoqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o perimentibus monendo, do cendo, hortan do terrendo, <hi>Aug. ver Dom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>8.</hi>
                     </note> we are to ſtirre up our ſelves againſt it, as farre as our calling and condition of life will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit. <hi>They that forſake the Law</hi> (<note n="t" place="margin">Pro. 28.4</note> ſaith <hi>Salomon) praiſe the wicked; but ſuch as keepe the Law, contend with them. The innocent ſhall ſtirre up himſelfe against the hypocrite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> ſaith <hi>Iob, Iob</hi> 17.8. They will not let them carry it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1858:60"/> ſo, but will reprove them for their wickedneſſe. The example of that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Governour <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> is remarkeable in this kinde; who contended with the Nobles who profaned the Sabbath day, and by their example drew on others to that grievous ſinne: Heare what he ſaith,<note n="u" place="margin">Neh. 13.17</note> 
                     <hi>Then conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded I with the Nobles of Iudah, and ſaid unto them; What evill thing is this that yee doe, and prophane the Sabbath day? Did not your fathers thus? and did not our God bring all this evill upon us, and upon the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? yet yee bring more wrath upon Iſrael, by prophaning the Sabbath.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Verſ. 28</note> See alſo how <hi>hee cleaſed from him one of the ſons of the high Priest, becauſe hee
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1858:60"/> was ſonne in law to Sanballat,</hi> who was a profeſſed enemy to Gods people, and a great ſcoffer at all their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings. But incomparable is the example of our Saviour in reforming the abuſes of the Temple;<note n="*" place="margin">Iohn 2.15</note> 
                     <hi>Zealous of his fathers houſe, he whipt out the buyers and ſellers, powred out the mony-changers, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the Tables:</hi> At which fact, <hi>the Diſciples remembred that it was written, The Zeale of thy houſe hath eaten me up.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 4.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves when we come to God in prayer.</head>
                  <p>VVE are alſo to exerciſe this ſtirringneſſe of
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:1858:61"/> heart in all duties of Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, whether they be duties of immediate worſhip, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe.</p>
                  <p>To give ſome inſtances:</p>
                  <p>When wee draw neere to the Lord to pray to him, it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves, and to declare by all ſignes<note n="x" place="margin">
                        <hi>Vitus Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon,</hi> ſpeakes thus of <hi>Luther,</hi> No day paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> him, faith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e, but he ſpent three houres at leaſt in prayer. Once I happened to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heare him being at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>rayer: O what ſpirit, and life, and faith, was there in his prayers! what hee aske, hee doth it with ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ch <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ce, as having to deale with God; with ſuch faith and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pe, as ſpeaking with hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Father, or his friend, <hi>In vit. Luth. pag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 142</note> our great deſire to be heard of him: God is of ſuch Majeſty, as he looks for all earneſtneſſe in our petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and the excellency, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the great need of the things deſired, ſhould move intention of all our powers in ſeeking them from God. S. <hi>Iames</hi>
                     <note n="y" place="margin">Jam. 5.16.</note> ſaith, <hi>that ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual prayer,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:1858:61"/> deprecation incitated, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven with motion, and force, vehement, fervent, with great affection of devotion)<note n="z" place="margin">Diligent prayer and the commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of ſinne wil not ſtand together for if prayer cannot make a man cea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e from ſinne, yet his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng will make him leave off praying, <hi>Mert. lib. t. page</hi> 61.</note> 
                     <hi>hath great force with God</hi> to obtaine that which wee deſire.<note n="a" place="margin">Acts 26.7</note> 
                     <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of the <hi>twelue Tribes,</hi> that <hi>they inſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſerved God day and night:</hi> the word is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, with intention of Spirit. This is ſometime called<note n="b" place="margin">2 Kin. 19.4</note> 
                     <hi>lifting up of a prayer:</hi> It is recorded to the great praiſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> that<note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 32.26 28 Hoſ. 12.3, 4</note> 
                     <hi>by his ſtrength hee had great power with God; yea, he had power over the Angell, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed; he wept, and made ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication unto him, hee found him in Bethel, and there hee ſpake with us.</hi> In which is ſet downe, both the favour of God to <hi>Iacob,</hi> vouchſafing
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1858:62"/> the manifeſtation of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and ſpeech with him; and the faith and piety of <hi>Iacob</hi> propounded to be imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tated by us, as belonging to our confirmation, who hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding faſt the promiſe made him at <hi>Bethel,</hi> wreſtled ſtrongly by the faith of it, and found that hee had not beleeved in vaine; at <hi>Bethel</hi> againe was the Promiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed unto him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 5.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in prayer for others.</head>
                  <p>SO when we ſeeke to him by prayer for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to others, it is our duty to quicken and enkindle in
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1858:62"/> our ſelves, ſtrong affections.<note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 18.13</note> 
                     <hi>Abraham</hi> was earneſt and importunate <hi>with God</hi> for wicked <hi>Sodom:</hi> eſpecially for ſuch as are neare and deare unto us; as the<note n="c" place="margin">Mat. 15.22, 23.</note> woman of <hi>Syropheniſſa</hi> obtained her requeſt in the behalfe of her child. But moſt eſpecially wee ſhould put forth all the ſtrength of our ſpirits in the behalfe of the Church and people of God: <hi>Yee chat bee Lords Remembrancers</hi> (<note n="f" place="margin">Iſa. 62.6, 7</note> ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah) keepe not ſilence, and give him no rest, nor hold thy peace day nor night, til he eſtabliſh and make Ieruſalem a praiſe in the earth.</hi> When Gods people were driven into great ſtreights, by reaſon of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his purſuing them behinde, and
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:1858:63"/> having the Red Sea before them, the Lord asked <hi>Moſes,</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">Exo. 14.15 Num. 14. 12 20</note> 
                     <hi>Why cryeſt thou unto me?</hi> Ah! <hi>Moſes</hi> could not hold his peace, but muſt burſt out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtrong prayers and cryes. <hi>Aaron</hi> alſo beſtirred him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, when the plague brake forth amongſt the people;<note n="h" place="margin">Num 16. 46 47</note> 
                     <hi>He ranne quickly, ſtood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the dead and the living and made attonement for the people:</hi> So interpoſing, and, as it were, expoſing himſelfe to the wrath of God for the people: It was not ſo much the Incenſe, as the ſtrong prayers of <hi>Aaron</hi> that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with God to ſtay the plague. So <hi>when Peter was in priſon,</hi> it is<note n="i" place="margin">Acts 12.5</note> ſayd, that <hi>Prayer was made of the Church with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ceaſing for him;</hi> (the word
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:1858:63"/> is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, earneſt and ſtretched-out prayer;) the Church was ſo earneſt with the Lord, that hee was faine to take him out of priſon, unlooſe his chaines, and bring him to them, and ſet him before them; as if the Lord had ſayd, there hee is, your importunity hath<note n="k" place="margin">Deus ipſe qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nullu cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſe virilus ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peraripoteſt pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cibus v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citur. <hi>Hiero</hi>
                     </note> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come me. O the power of fervent-conjoyned prayers! Theſe bee the<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Prece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſunt Bombard<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> &amp; inſtrument<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian rum.</hi> uther. <hi>Arius</hi> the heretike was b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ht to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> by th p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the good Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eath w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, <hi>precationis opus non morbi.</hi> Socra, lib. 1 cap 15.</note> ſcaling-ladders that are ſet up to heaven; and theſe doe lay ſiege to the Throne of God, and encompaſſe him round, and will not depart till they have that they came for.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:1858:64"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 6.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in prayſing God.</head>
                  <p>VVHen we draw neare to prayſe him for bleſſings, received, having therein a comfortable taſte of Gods love to us, that he is our God, and we his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves in all the heights and elevations of our hearts, that poſſibly we may: Hence have proceeded thoſe high ſtraines of ſpeech, and<note n="l" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ebullit Cor.</hi> Pſal. 45.1</note> ebul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litions of the hearts of Gods ſervants.<note n="m" place="margin">Iudg. 5.12</note> 
                     <hi>Deborah,</hi> to her due prayſing of God, calls upon her ſelfe <hi>to awake, to ſing a ſong;</hi> and the redoubling
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1858:64"/> of the word, <hi>Awake, awake, Deborah, awake, awake to utter a Song,</hi> implyeth her care to doe it with all, her might. So <hi>David,</hi>
                     <note n="n" place="margin">Pſa. 57, 7, 8</note> 
                     <hi>My heart is fixed, O God, my heart is fixed:</hi> which noteth the addicting of himſelfe, with conſtant purpoſe of minde, to the duty of prayſing God, and alſo his alacrity wherewith he comes to it, not only op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to hypocriſie, but to torpor and ſpirit-leſneſſe; kindled with zeale, he ſhoo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> off all impediments, to bee attentive to this voluntary Sacrifice; which the verſe following declares; <hi>Aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ke up my glory, awake up Lute and Harpe;</hi> expreſſing the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemency of his heart, and burning deſire, hee ſtirres up
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:1858:65"/> his tongue, and joynes the helpe of Inſtruments to fire himſelfe the more. In ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Pſalme</hi> he ſtirres up<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 101, 1 <hi>Habet e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Cor,</hi> Aug. ad loc.</note> 
                     <hi>all that is within him;</hi> he cals, as it were, a Council, aſſembles all his powers, and<note n="p" place="margin">Zeph. 3.14 Zach. 9.9</note> faculties of ſoule, underſtanding, will, affections, in their full ſtrength, to this duty of prayſing God It falls out ſometimes, that when the ſoule is in ſerious contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of Gods mercies paſt, preſent, and to come, that the fire ſecretly kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, and a man burſts out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to high prayſes of God, fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his tongue to come far ſhort of his heart, and his heart infinitely too narrow to comprehend, either the multitude of ſo many mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1858:65"/> or the great love of him that is the beſtower of them and ſo he is ſwallowed up in that Sea which hath neither banke nor bottome, but is faine to cry out, <hi>O the depth, the depth, the depth!</hi> and can goe no farther: and this is the higheſt manner of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing God, though one can ſpeake never a word more.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 7.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in ſtanding for God and his honour.</head>
                  <p>IN our ſtanding for God, promoting his honour, and exalting his name, it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves, and that not onely by
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:1858:66"/> ſpreading the knowledge of him in our owne hearts, and ſetting, him up as glorious there, making al things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in us to ſtoope and doe low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obeyſance to him, by<note n="a" place="margin">Jam. 4.12</note> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging his authority in what hee commands, and<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ, 119.128</note> by keeping the heart in a continuall readineſſe to ſet about what ſhal be comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded us from him, and<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 42.5, 6 1 Sam. 3.9</note> by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in his will when it is revealed,<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 1.15, 16. Heb. 11.8</note> without reſiſting or gaine-ſaying, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by a faithfull dependance upon him, and hanging up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him from day to day, as a childe upon the mothers breſt, by all which wee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance, and lift up the Lord in our hearts; but alſo when wee are ready to make an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:1858:66"/> profeſſion of him, not fearing the face of man, when Gods cauſe comes in queſtion. Then a man is right in his way, when hee gives up himſelfe to bee wholly for God, when al his ends, projects, and purpoſes are ſubſervient and ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate unto him and his glory. We read of <hi>Caleb,</hi> that when the falſe Spyes<note n="e" place="margin">Num. 13, 28.30</note> diſcouraged the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from entring into <hi>Canaan,</hi> by telling them of Cities walled up to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and of the Gyants the children of <hi>Anak,</hi> his ſpirit was mightily ſtirred, and he ſayd,<note n="f" place="margin">Num. 14, 8</note> 
                     <hi>Let us goe up at once, if the Lord delight in us, he will bring us into this Land.</hi> For which ſtanding in Gods cauſe, the Lord gives this
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:1858:67"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:1858:67"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="112" facs="tcp:1858:68"/> teſtimony of him, That<note n="g" place="margin">
                        <hi>Num. 14.24</hi> Ad verbum implevit poſt me.</note> 
                     <hi>he had another ſpirit with him;</hi> and, <hi>that he hath followed mee fully.</hi> The Hebrew word is a metaphor taken from a Shippe under ſayle, which is carried ſtrongly with the wind, as if it feared neither rockes nor ſands. <hi>Iehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat</hi> alſo<note n="h" place="margin">1 Chr. 17.6</note> 
                     <hi>had his heart lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted up in the wayes of God:</hi> he was more couragious and bold in promoting the true worſhip of God, than <hi>Aſa</hi> his father was: With a high Spirit he tooke away Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; contemning perill, hee tooke away the high places and groves, which either his father left, or the people in the latter end of his reigne brought in againe. <hi>David,</hi> but a youth, was mightily
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:1858:68"/> ſtirred up in Gods cauſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Goliah railed on the hoaſt of the living God, thy</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">1 Sam. 17.32.48</note> 
                     <hi>ſervant</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>wil go &amp; fight with this Philistim:</hi> drawing neere him to fight, <hi>hee hasted and ranne,</hi> moved with fervent zeale, to be avenged on the blaſphemy of Gods name. It is ſaid of <hi>Baruch,</hi> in the repayring of the wall of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, he</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Neh. 3.20 <hi>Se occendit</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>repayred earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> or as ſome read it, he fired himſelfe, burſt out into heat, angry with himſelfe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, that were ſo ſlothfull in working, ſo finiſhed his portion in a ſhorter time. This ſtirringneſſe of Spirit did appeare in <hi>Levi,</hi> who preferred Gods glory to all naturall affection,<note n="l" place="margin">Deut. 33.9</note> 
                     <hi>Who ſayd to his Father and his Mother, I
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:1858:69"/> have not ſeene him, neither knew hee his owne brethren, or his owne children; for they obſerved thy word, and kept thy Commandement.</hi> Thus alſo have the holy Confeſſours and bleſſed Martyrs done, whoſe Spirits wee ſhould deſire to be dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled upon us, in theſe evill and backe-ſliding dayes; who living incurſt and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell times, in Gods cauſe and for his ſake<note n="m" place="margin">Rev. 12.11</note> 
                     <hi>loved not their lives unto the death,</hi> but thought the priſon<note n="a" place="margin">Who will ever beleeve that I ſhall ſay? or what man will e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thinke? in the deepe darke dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon to find a paradiſe of pleaſure in the place of ſorrow; and to dwell in tranquillity, and hope of life in a cave infernall to be found ioy of ſoule: where other men doe ſhake and tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble, there ſtrength and boldneſſe to be plenty? <hi>Algerid</hi> his letter, <hi>Fox, Act. &amp; Mon. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ol,</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 181.</note> a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and great iron chaines great<note n="b" place="margin">
                        <hi>Marſac</hi> go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the ſtake to be burned, with two others with ropes about their neckes, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe to be ſpared by reaſon of his order and degree, deſired to have one of thoſe precious chaines about his necke, in honour of his Lord, <hi>Fox, ib. p.</hi> 141. <hi>Luther</hi> reſolved to appeare at <hi>Wormes,</hi> though all the tyles on the houſes ſhould be Divels.</note> ornaments, and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced the flames as cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully as <hi>Eliah</hi> did the fiery
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:1858:69"/> Chariot, that came to fetch him to heaven. O when the love of their deereſt Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer had once warmed their hearts, they were mightily inflamed, and like <hi>Davids three Worthies,</hi> who for <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> ſake, brake through the hoaſt of the <hi>Philistims;</hi> ſo theſe were ready, for his ſake to undergoe all hard adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to looke all dangers in the face, and to breake tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row an hoaſt of Deaths and Devils.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="section">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:1858:70"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 8.</hi> About ſtirring up ourſelves in the reading and hearing Gods holy Word.</head>
                  <p>IN regard of Gods holy word, when wee are to be exerciſed in the reading of it, or hearing it preached, or read, it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves: as,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. In reading the holy Scriptures: when thou ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keſt up the Bible into thy hand to read, looke upon it, as upon the moſt bleſſed booke that ever eye ſaw, and that no booke in the world hath that in it,<note n="c" place="margin">Quid eſt Scriptura ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cra nifi quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam Epiſtola omnipotentis Dei ad crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turam ſuam, <hi>Greg.</hi>
                     </note> which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes thee ſo much, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in it the whole counſell
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:1858:70"/> of God for thy good. And as children are ſtirring and wakefull when they heare their fathers Will reade, to know and underſtand what is left them there; ſo ought wee to ſtirre up our ſelves, conſidering thoſe many rich and precious Legacies which our Savior hath bequeathed unto us, in that laſt Will and Teſtament of his, ſealed with his owne blood.</p>
                  <p>So in hearing the Word read, wee have a notable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in <hi>Ezra</hi> his time, that<note n="n" place="margin">Nch. 8.3</note> 
                     <hi>when hee read in the booke of the Law, from morning to mid-day, the eares of all the people were attentive to the booke of the Law.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. In hearing the Word Preached, it is our duty to
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1858:71"/> ſtirre up ourſelves with all the life of attention we may; as hearing the Lord ſpeaking in his Servants: Hither tend thoſe preſſing exhortations in Scripture, <hi>To</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Iſay 55.3</note> 
                     <hi>incline the eare; To be</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">Jam. 1.19</note> 
                     <hi>ſwiſt to heare; Flying,</hi> to the places of aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, <hi>as</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 60.8</note> 
                     <hi>Doves to their windowes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Bereans</hi> are commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for this, that they heard the Word,<note n="r" place="margin">Acts 16.11</note> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> with all readineſſe and ala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crity. In hearing the Word, we are <hi>to</hi>
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 24.7</note> 
                     <hi>lift up theſe everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sting doores,</hi> to ſet wide open the doores of our hearts, <hi>that the King of glory may come in.</hi> We are to chooſe the Word <hi>as our</hi>
                     <note n="t" place="margin">Pſal. 119.111.173</note> 
                     <hi>portion,</hi> for the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, beauty, and truth of it. To bring hearts and affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:1858:71"/> anſwerable to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in hand; when the Lord threatens, to bring feare; when he promiſeth, to bring<note n="u" place="margin">Neh. 8.12</note> joy; to<note n="*" place="margin">2 Chro. 34 27. Luke 3.10</note> yeeld willingly to the ſtampe of every truth, as the Wax to the Seale. To ſet the heart ſtrongly to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very word of God,<note n="x" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. 1 Tim. 4.15</note> clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving inſeparably to every truth, binding them cloſe to the ſoule.<note n="y" place="margin">Deu. 32.46</note> 
                     <hi>Set your hearts,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Moſes) to all the words which I teſtifie amongſt you this day, which you ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand your children to obſerve to doe all the words of this Law, for it is not a vaine thing for you, becauſe it is your life, and through this you ſhall prolong your dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. For Miniſters, and ſuch as are to preach the Word, it
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:1858:72"/> is their duty to<note n="z" place="margin">In Bucholſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro vivida om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia fuerunt, vt vida vox, vivida oculi, vividae manus geſtus omnes vividi. <hi>Mel. ad in vit. ipſe p. 556.</hi>
                     </note> ſtirre up themſelves in the carefull diſcharge of this their weighty calling.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Names given in Scripture, doe all imply la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boriouſneſſe, and great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention: They are called<note n="a" place="margin">Ezec. 3.17</note> Watchmen,<note n="b" place="margin">Ier, 23.4</note> Shepheards,<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.10</note> Builders,<note n="d" place="margin">Mal. 3.1</note> Meſſengers,<note n="e" place="margin">Tit. 1.7</note> Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Their worke ſet them, as dealing with the precious ſoules of men, and to call home wandring loſt ſinners, cals for ſo much. They are to <hi>Preach with all</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Acts 18.2-28.</note> 
                     <hi>diligence,</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.2</note> 
                     <hi>earnestneſſe, and inſtancy; in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon;</hi> with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and freedome of ſpirit,<note n="h" place="margin">Iſa. 58.1 Ier. 28.17</note> 
                     <hi>feareleſſe of the face of man:</hi> With great<note n="i" place="margin">Phil. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.8</note> earneſt deſire of the ſalvation of Men, and
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:1858:72"/> the people committed to them. This made the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to enter into <hi>great</hi>
                     <note n="k" place="margin">Col. 2.1</note> 
                     <hi>conflicts and combatings</hi> for the <hi>Coloſsians,</hi> and to bee pained and afflicted as a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 4.19</note> travell.</p>
                  <p>O me thinkes what ſhould not one doe to keepe one ſoule from periſhing everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtingly! if any<note n="m" place="margin">Hic eſt ille Farellus qui nullis difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatibus fractus nullis minus convitiis, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beribus deni<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> inflictus teri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, Mempel-garoenſes A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>enſes. Lauſanenſes, Gene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſes, Noacomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Chriſto Lucrifecit. <hi>M l. Adam Decad. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Farel.</hi> p. 115.</note> paynes and ſtudy would doe it; if deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a mans credit, profit, pleaſure, and eaſe would doe it; if ſtooping, and yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and laying our hands under their feet would do it. if prayers and teares would doe it; or if, like Clouds, we ſhould ſweat our ſelves to death, ſo ſoules might bee brought home to God, it were a bleſſed way of dying.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="section">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:1858:73"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 9.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in Meditation.</head>
                  <p>THe minde being quie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and compoſed, and deepe ſilence and attention being cauſed in the whole man, thy ſpirit being awed with the preſence of God, draw forth the ſubject mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter thou wouldſt meditate of, and to ſtirre thee up in the duty, take theſe two helpes:</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in things that are good, and of a divine and heavenly nature, <hi>labour to ſee them at their beſt,</hi> preſent them to thy ſelfe in their prime and beauty. To give
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:1858:73"/> ſome Inſtances:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If thou wouldſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of God, labour to ſee him in the glory of his At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes, as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 34.5, 6.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. If thou wouldſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate of Chriſt, ay me at the higheſt and moſt raiſed ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions of his excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy; ſee him in his Nature, and Offices, or hanging on the Croſſe, or ſitting at the right hand of God, as <hi>Steven</hi> ſaw him, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.55. and <hi>Iſa. chap.</hi> 9. view him in thoſe places wherein <hi>Paul</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents him, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. and <hi>Col.</hi> 1.13. to 21.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If thou wouldſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of heaven, and the glory of it, labour by the eye of faith to penetrate into it, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:1858:74"/> to ſee it at the beſt, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaw it, being caught up into the third heaven, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.12. and as <hi>Peter</hi> repreſents it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.4.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. If thou wouldſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of Gods Love to thee in Chriſt; See it at the beſt, in the dimenſions of it, in the bredth, length, heighth, and depth of it, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.18, 19. Thinke from whence thou art brought, to what things advanced; thy ſelfe digged out of the rubbiſh, and ruines of forlorne man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, and placed as a <hi>living ſtone in Gods building;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.5</note> as a <hi>brand pluckt out of the fire,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Zach. 3.2</note> and like <hi>Ionah,</hi> from the bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of hell, caſt up upon the dry land, and made a childe of God, and heire of life.</p>
                  <p n="5">
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:1858:74"/>5. If thou wouldſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate on the Promiſes, looke on them at their beſt, as moſt freſh, and greene, as they grow out of the heart of God, and breſt of Chriſt, their native and proper ſeat; out of whom they are but as fading and dying things. They being in their full ſtrength and vigor as ever, the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever; what Gods people have hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore found them to bee, they are ſtill the ſame unto us; <hi>like ſilver tryed and purified ſeven times,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſnl. 12.6</note> and have as much life and comfort in them as formerly in <hi>Abrahams,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Heb. 11.13</note> or in <hi>Davids</hi> time; what ever they could ſpeake of them, Gods people in this age of
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:1858:75"/> the world are able to report the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, if thou wouldſt meditate on things which are in their nature ſimply evill, <hi>labour to ſee them at their worst.</hi> Take for inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:</p>
                  <p n="1">1. If thou wouldſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate of ſinne, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of it, ſee it at its worſt, even worſe than the Divell himſelfe; for what made him a Divell but ſinne? it was ſinne ſpoyled him; he was a glorious Angell till hee was acquainted with ſinne. Thinke it is that which is moſt contrary to the moſt holy Nature of God, and is the ſole Object of all his hatred; whereas his love is diſperſed to ſeverall things,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:1858:75"/> his Selfe, his Sonne, his Children, &amp;c. Thinke it is that which makes the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt ſeparation betweene God and us, and to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out God in this world, which onely makes a man accurſed, which all miſeries of themſelves can never doe. This blots out the Image of God, ſtamped on us at our firſt Creation, which being loſt, all Paradiſe could not make <hi>Adam</hi> happy. This conformes us to the Image of the Divell, and cauſeth us to have communion with him, who is Gods greateſt enemy: This is it that grieves Gods moſt Holy Spirit, and ſends him ſad to heaven, when wee reſiſt his motions, and ruſh into evill.</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:1858:76"/>2. If thou wouldſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate of Gods wrath, looke upon it as at the worſt; as it keepes burning and glow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe everlaſting flames, and can blow the coales of a thouſand hels more; the leaſt ſparke of which let fall into the Conſcience ſets all on a flame, which without the ſprinkling of Chriſts blood, and the teares of true Repentance, can never bee quenched.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If thou wouldſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate of the ſtate of a ſoule that is loſt, thinke of it as at worſt; even as of a forlorne, helpeleſſe, hopeleſſe crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, covered with ſhame and horror, and lying amidſt the pangs, throbs, &amp; throws of guiltineſſe, which is <hi>the
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:1858:76"/> Worme that never dyes;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mark. 9.44</note> of whom all mercy, pitty, and comfort have taken their leaves for ever, being there to remaine in that dungeon of fire ſo long as Hel is Hel, and God is God.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 10.</hi> How we ſhould ſtirre up our ſelves in ſanctifying the Lords day.</head>
                  <p>IN ſanctifying the Lords day it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves, both in long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for it before it comes, and highly prizing it when it is come;<note n="n" place="margin">Iſa. 58.23</note> 
                     <hi>making it the ioy and reioycing of our hearts.</hi> It is recorded of the godly Jewes, before our Saviours
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:1858:77"/> time, that they called the Sabbath,<note n="o" place="margin">Wemeſ. Chriſt. Syn. p. <hi>76.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Deſiderium dierum</hi> the deſire of dayes, the moſt deſired day. Every moment of this day ſhould bee preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, as having Gods bleſſing more immediately annexed unto it, and unto all thoſe duties performed in it; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, as it were, his Image and Superſcription more lively portrayed, and engra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven upon it; and therefore to be improued by us to our uttermoſt, in all the parts and duties of that day.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="section">
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:1858:77"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 11.</hi> How wee are to ſtirre up our ſelves in our partaking of the Sacraments.</head>
                  <p>IN the uſe of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, it is our duty to ſtir up our ſelves:</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. In regard of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of Baptiſme,<note place="margin">How to ſtir up our ſerve to make uſe of our bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme to our ſelves and our children</note> both to our ſelves, and our chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and that in theſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. By calling to minde what wee, and our children are by nature, <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of wrath;</hi> both wee and they, all of us (like ſtill-borne children) borne<note n="p" place="margin">Epheſ. 2.3</note> 
                     <hi>dead in treſpaſſes and ſinnes,</hi>
                     <note n="q" place="margin">Ezec. 16.6</note> wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring in the blood of the ſins of our firſt parents, empty of
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:1858:78"/> all grace, prone to all wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, though as then not able to put it forth in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Act, no more then young Vipers, or then the Cubs of wild beaſts; which yet, when wee grow up to ripeneſſe and ſtrength, are ready to breake forth to doe any miſchiefe, if wee be not reſtrayned. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. By intere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting our ſelves, and our children in the Covenant of Promiſe, whereof Baptiſme is the Seale. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> This is done by dedicating and reſigning up our ſelves, and them, to be Gods people; as Hee, in the Covenant,<note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 17.7,</note> offereth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to bee a God to us, and ours; and withall praying for our ſelves, and them, that we, and they <hi>might</hi>
                     <note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 17.18</note> 
                     <hi>live
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:1858:78"/> in his ſight.</hi> How ſhould it provoke us to wreſtle with God, to convey a Covenant and Sacrament of life unto our children, ſince wee have conveyed to them nothing but ſinne, and wrath, and the fruit of both, which is death. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. By growing up our ſelves, and training up our children to keepe the Covenant on our parts, that the Lord may delight to<note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 8.19</note> bring the bleſſing of the Covenant upon us and ours. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. By walking in the purity of Gods Ordinances, with a pure and an honeſt heart: for want of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, Gods wrath burſt forth againſt <hi>Gedeons</hi> children, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 8 27. and againſt <hi>Eli</hi> and his, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 3.13. For want of the latter, againſt <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maziah,</hi>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:1858:79"/> 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 2 5.2. which <hi>David</hi> ſought to prevent, by giving his ſonne <hi>Salomon</hi> better counſell, 1 <hi>Chr.</hi> 28.9</p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. In receiving the Lords Supper,<note place="margin">How to ſtir up ourſelves in the right uſe of the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per.</note> it is our duty to ſtir up our ſelves, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1. By conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the great need we ſtand in of ſuch an Ordinance: what need Chriſt to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced to us, as <hi>Bread</hi> to ſtrengthen us, and <hi>Wine</hi> to quicken us, if we were not of our ſelves weake, and dull, and even ſtarved creatures without him? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2.<note n="u" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.28</note> By exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and ſearching out the feebleneſſe of our beſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and the ſtrength of our manifold corruptions; that ſo as by ſearching into the ſores and wounds of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, the body is payned and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:1858:79"/> grieved; ſo by ſearching in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſores and wounds of our ſoules, our hearts may be inwardly pricked and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 3. By reforming our ſelves and our families be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee come to partake in this Supper: For if wee bee uncircumciſed our ſelves, we diſcovenant our ſelves and them; as on the contrary, if the Maſter of the Family bee a true beleever, the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is made with him, and his houſhold: There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when <hi>Zacheus</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, Chriſt ſayd, <hi>This day is Salvation come to this houſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Luke 19.9</note> 
                     <hi>for as much as hee alſo is the Sonne of Abraham.</hi> And hence wee read in the <hi>Acts,</hi> when the maſter of a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was turned to the faith,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:1858:80"/> that he was baptized and his whole houſhold; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore alſo it lyes upon us not to leave them at home; ſo, nor to bring them with us uncircumciſed, ſo farre as it lyes in us to uſe the means for their good, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.48. Chriſt was carefull to<note n="a" place="margin">1 Ioh. 13, 8 10.</note> waſh his Diſciples feet, to purifie their hearts againſt the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Such <hi>new wine,</hi> as Chriſt is, <hi>would bee put into new bottles.</hi> 
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 4. By beholding Chriſt in the Sacrament, as it were crucified before our eyes, that we might mourne the more ſeriouſly in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the ſins, by which we have pierced<note n="b" place="margin">Zac. 12.10.</note> him <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> 5. By admiring at the wonderfull goodneſſe of God to our ſoules; who when we were
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:1858:80"/> as<note n="c" place="margin">2 Sam. 9.8 with 19.28</note> 
                     <hi>dead dogge</hi> (as <hi>Mephibo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth</hi> ſaid to <hi>David</hi>) yet the Lord is pleaſed to ſet us at his owne Table, to feed us with the Body and Blood of his owne Sonne, and thereby to make us one body and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit with his Sonne, giving him to us, and us to him, that wee might partake in all the precious bleſſings hee hath purchaſed for us, both for this life, and for a better, and therefore we are to feed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him with faith, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding joy for all his abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant goodneſſe to us herein. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> 6. By ſetting up Chriſt (whole Chriſt) in our hearts as our King, Prieſt, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet; that he, being received into us, may rule us, and teach us, and pacifie us, and
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:1858:81"/> purifie us, and<note n="f" place="margin">Gal. 2.20</note> live our whole life in us. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly, by cleaving the more to our brethren in al love and deare affection, whom wee ſee to communicate with us in the ſame Chriſt;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.17 2 Cor. 12.13</note> and called of God to partake in the ſame Table with us.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 12.</hi> How to ſtirre up our ſelves in laying hold on the Promiſes.</head>
                  <p>IT is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves, to conceive confidence in our hearts in taking hold of God, as hee hath offered himſelfe in his Covenant, &amp; Promiſes (the ſpeciall thing mentioned here in the Text) and a point
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:1858:81"/> of great uſe through the whole courſe of our lives: on which I ſhal a little more inſiſt; opening the phraſe what it is <hi>to take hold on God,</hi> and ſhewing how the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture calleth for this duty. The phraſe is put for the Act of beleeving, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is to bee performed by the whole man, and all the powers of it, and is the great Act of all others, and includes all others, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is ſet forth to us in Scripture by all the ſeverall Acts of each member or faculty in a man: So, elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where it is called <hi>Seeing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.3</note> performing the Office of the eye to the ſoule; <hi>Eating,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Iſay 30.7</note> 
                     <hi>tasting, comming to Christ, ſitting ſtill;</hi> and here (to
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:1858:82"/> name no more) <hi>Taking hold of God,</hi> performing the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the hand, it being all in all to the ſoule. Thus, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.2. God promiſing <hi>to bring neare his righteouſneſſe and ſalvation, and to place it in Sion for Iſrael his glory;</hi> he addeth, <hi>Bleſſed is the Sonne of Man that takes hold of it;</hi> that is, any mortall man, be hee Jew or ſtranger; which was firſt in fulfilling his Promiſe to reſtore the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> but prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the righteouſneſſe declared in Chriſt and his Salvation: And <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. it is called <hi>taking hold of the Covenant;</hi> that is, beleeving. Faith then is the hand wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by God is to bee layed hold upon; God in himſelfe, as
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:1858:82"/> he cannot be ſeene, ſo nor be layed hold of by the hand of any mortall man, but hath ſubjected himſelfe to the capacity and apprehenſion of faith, by ſetting forth his Sonne and Promiſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene us and him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, as by two Handles, wee lay hold on that God, whom the world in the darke feeles after, and cannot finde, <hi>Acts</hi> 17.27.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, his Sonne; and therefore faith is expreſſed to us by apprehending Chriſt, <hi>Philip.</hi> 3.12. and thus the Church, being in Temptation of Unbeleefe, after ſhee had found Chriſt for attonement, ſhee <hi>layed hold on him, Cant.</hi> 3.4. <hi>and would not let him goe.</hi> And
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:1858:83"/> ſo laying hold on Chriſt, wee have <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, are led by the hand to God, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3.12.</p>
                  <p>And ſecondly, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; therefore, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. the Patriarchs are ſayd by faith to have received the Promiſes, and to have <hi>embraced them:</hi> So as firſt wee take hold of the Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and of Chriſt in them, and then by this meanes we come to God, having both hope and faith in him, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.21. The life of faith then lyes in apprehenſion, and application of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and of God therein. The Covenant ſayes, <hi>I will bee a God to them, and they ſhall bee a people to mee.</hi> Firſt, indeed God ſpeakes to the
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:1858:83"/> ſoules of men, <hi>Thou art my people;</hi> and then they lay hold on him, ſaying, <hi>And the Lord is my God.</hi> As in our firſt ſeperation from the world, by Divine Calling, wee ſtand up, and take hold of him for the obtaining of reconciliation, and all other bleſſings flowing from hence in Jeſus Chriſt, ſo wee goe on after in our life, ſeeking by increaſe of faith to enjoy him more and more, and apprehend him for the bleſſing of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, whereunto our ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall Calling gave us Title: That as all bleſſings that wee enjoy with his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour proceed from him, as declaring himſelfe to bee our God; as bleſſings<note n="a" place="margin">Exod. 6.7</note> earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:1858:84"/>
                     <note n="b" place="margin">Heb. 8.10.</note> ſpirituall and<note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 11.16</note> heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; ſo in our neceſſities, we renew our faith of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, <hi>I will be thy God;</hi> and plead our intereſt in him for obtaining all bleſſings, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding him faſt; as, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.4. <hi>I am thine, ſave mee:</hi> and the Peophet here, <hi>verſ.</hi> 8, 9. Thus <hi>David, Pſalm.</hi> 43.2. <hi>Thou art the God of my ſtrength, why dost thou cast mee off?</hi> and, <hi>verſ.</hi> 5. <hi>My ſoule hope in God, for I ſhall yet prayſe him, who is the health of my countenance, and my God:</hi> And thus are wee eſpecially to take hold of God in evill times (to which this Text eſpecially referres this duty) when Gods hand is ſtretched out againſt our ſelves, and the Church. So,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:1858:84"/> 
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 27.4, 5. when God goes through his Church, bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning up the briars &amp; thorns, to prevent which, hee bids a man take hold of his ſtrength; that is, by faith hold his hands. As when a man is lifting up his hand to ſtrike, another ſteps in, and layes hold on it, and ſtayes him, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did when Gods wrath was gone out againſt the Iſraelites: <hi>Let mee alone,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Deut. 9.14</note> ſaith God; which if a man doth, God promiſeth in the following words, that <hi>hee ſhall make peace with him, for fury is not in mee.</hi> When the Lord ſeemes to bee furious, yet faith laying hold, hath power with him to ſtay his hand; though it bee his <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and the hand of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:1858:85"/> faith weake in it ſelfe, yet it ſhall have power with him, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 12.3. And then when hee beginnes to with-draw himſelfy, as it were, we are to excite our faith, draw neere, and take hold of him. <hi>Oh be not farre from mee, for trouble is neare,</hi> ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 22.11. As a childe if hee bee to goe in the darke, or in a crowd, hee will bee ſure to take faſt hold of his father, and not leave him. And becauſe wee are natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally dull unto this, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee muſt ſtirre up our ſelves to it. Other things, as Riches, &amp;c. are, <hi>ad manum,</hi> nigh us here below; and therefore like dying men, that catch hold on any thing that is next them, ſo doe we
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:1858:85"/> on theſe to helpe us, and do truſt in them. But God, and Chriſt, they are high, and farre above our ſight and naturall reach, and therefore wee are loth to ſtretch to them, to lay hold on them, and muſt ſtirre up our ſelves to it.</p>
                  <p>Thus having explicated the phraſe, and ſhewed the duty, I ſhall briefly ſhew how wee are to ſtirre up our faith to make uſe of the Promiſes to our ſelves, and lay hold on them, and God by them, which is done di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers wayes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, by knowing that wee are the children of the Promiſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.8. ſo called becauſe the Promiſes per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to us, <hi>verſ.</hi> 4. So as
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:1858:86"/> knowing our ſelves chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, we may call the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ours; They are the <hi>childrens bread;</hi> and we may lay hold on them as our <hi>owne mercies, Ion:</hi> 2.8. All the Children of God being in this caſe, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> was, the Seed of the Promiſe; all of us borne of a word of faith: and as wee are borne of a Promiſe,<note place="margin">Rom. 10.17</note> ſo to all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are wee borne; yea, being in this right accounted one with Chriſt. Therefore <hi>Gal</hi> 3 16. to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed were the Promiſes made; to Seed <hi>as of one, which is Christ;</hi> that is, Chriſt myſtical, the whole Church.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, by conſidering that God hath given us his owne Sonne,<note n="y" place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cor. 1.20</note> in whom all
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:1858:86"/> the Promiſes are wrapped up and fulfilled; and<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 8.32</note> for whoſe ſake God will deny us nothing: We having mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the heire, have a joynt Title to his Inheritance, and the Deeds of it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, by obſerving the uprightneſſe of our harts to take the Commandements, and threatnings as due to us; and hee that maketh conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to take the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements as his <hi>Way,</hi> and the threatnings as his <hi>Bridle,</hi> hee may ſafely take all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes for his Inheritance and comfort.<note place="margin">Pſa. 119.111 112.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, by conſidering the free grace of God, in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and fulfilling his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, not for any worth in us,<note n="z" place="margin">Iſa. 43.25</note> but for his Name ſake:
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:1858:87"/>
                     <note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 32.10</note> acknowledging our owne unworthineſſe of the leaſt of all the promiſes and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of God, which make our empty veſſels more fit to receive them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly and laſtly, by me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditating on the Promiſes themſelves, pondering and muſing upon them: Whence the Spirit of Chriſt, beheld in the Promiſe, is conveyed unto us,<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 3.18</note> to transforme us into the likeneſſe of Chriſt by it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="section">
                  <pb n="151" facs="tcp:1858:87"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 13.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in duties of Love and Mercy.</head>
                  <p>THus of ſome Duties which have a more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Relation unto God, about which wee ought to ſtirre up our ſelves, now to goe forward, and to inſtance in ſome duties which have reference to our ſelves or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
                  <p>In all workes of Love and Mercy towards others, it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves, <hi>that wee</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">2 Theſ. 1.3</note> 
                     <hi>abound in them;</hi> and wee ſhould have<note n="d" place="margin">2 Cor. 8.16</note> 
                     <hi>an earneſt care about them;</hi> whether it bee in regard of the bodies, or ſoules of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers,
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:1858:88"/> or any other way. Our <hi>love ſhould be</hi>
                     <note n="e" place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1.3</note> 
                     <hi>laborious ful of the</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Rom. 12.10</note> 
                     <hi>bowels of tenderneſſe,</hi> and compaſſion; <hi>to be kindly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctioned,</hi> to <hi>be</hi>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">1 Tim 6.18</note> 
                     <hi>ready to diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute, willing to communicate.</hi> Where we ſee grace in any eminency to have our hearts knit to ſuch,<note n="h" place="margin">1 Sa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 18.1, 2</note> as <hi>Ionathans</hi> was to <hi>David.</hi>
                     <note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 10.24</note> 
                     <hi>To conſider one another, and to provoke to love, and good workes.</hi> Some we may finde in ſoule trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, with<note n="k" place="margin">Nehe. 2.2 Gen. 40.6, 7</note> countenances ſad and dejected, faces pale and wan, heavy-eyed, and ſighing as they goe, now to ſtirre up our ſelves to come to their<note n="i" place="margin">Iob 4.4</note> help and ſuccour, by all the wayes wee can: if it bee thy friend, or any thou canſt any way reach, never give thy ſelfe reſt, but let it
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:1858:88"/> pitty thy very heart, cry to God for their eaſe and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance, and if God have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven thee the skill of a Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Phyſician, with a ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der hand bind up the bruiſed Spirit. Some alſo are<note n="m" place="margin">Rom. 14.1</note> 
                     <hi>weake in faith,</hi> theſe wee ſhould ſupport: Some <hi>are feeble-minded,</hi> apt to bee diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, theſ.<note n="n" place="margin">1 The. 5.14</note> 
                     <hi>to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthen.</hi> Some are <hi>overtaken</hi> with frilings and temptations, <hi>theſe to</hi>
                     <note n="o" place="margin">Gal 6.1 <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>ſet aright,</hi> as a bone that was out of his place, as the word there ſignifies: ſome <hi>grow diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orderly,</hi> and ſcandalous, theſe <hi>to</hi>
                     <note n="p" place="margin">1 The. 5 14</note> 
                     <hi>reprove:</hi> ſome grow cold, luke-warme, and are like to<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 12.15</note> fall away, theſe to quicken and rowſe up from their drowſineſſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="section">
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:1858:89"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 14.</hi> Of ſtirring up our ſelves in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our Christian race.</head>
                  <p>IN regard of our Chriſtian race we are ſet to run, it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves,<note n="r" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.13</note> 
                     <hi>to gird up the loynes of our minde,</hi> to runne like the two Diſciples to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Sepulcher, who ranne with all their might, who ſhould come thither firſt: Wee ſhould not ſtay for company in this weighty bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe,<note n="ſ" place="margin">Quoties co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitas de per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festione vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutum noli conſiderare quid alii mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> habeant quam tu ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>, ſed quid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s minus ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, quam ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere iam de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bes. <hi>Filg.</hi>
                     </note> neither are wee to content our ſelves with the pace of carnall profeſſors, temporary beleevers, or la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zy Chriſtians; nor with that pace which wee our ſelves
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:1858:89"/> do, or have gone; nor ſhould wee looke backe to ſee who comes after, but thinke thou art upon life and death; therefore<note n="t" place="margin">Heb. 12.1</note> 
                     <hi>to caſt away every weight, and the ſinne that doth ſo eaſily beſet us;</hi> nothing in the world ſhould cauſe us to ſtep aſide, <hi>but to runne</hi>
                     <note n="u" place="margin">Pro 4.25</note> 
                     <hi>forth right:</hi> Wee <hi>ſhould now</hi>
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 3.13</note> 
                     <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get all things that are behinde reaching out to the things which are before.</hi> To this end we ſhould ſet before us, that<note n="x" place="margin">Heb. 12.1</note> 
                     <hi>cloud of witneſſes,</hi> thoſe bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſervants of God, who have gone before us, who <hi>have finiſhed their courſe, and kept the faith</hi> to their lateſt breath; eſpecially<note n="y" place="margin">Heb. 12 2</note> 
                     <hi>looking to Ieſus, the Author and finiſher of our faith; who, for the ioy that was ſet before him, endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:1858:90"/> the croſſe, deſpiſing the ſhame, and is ſet downe at the right hand of the Throne of God.</hi> Our Savior Chriſt is not as a dead marke,<note place="margin">Note.</note> who helpes not the runners at al, but loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king to him by faith, he gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth us in our way with his eye,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.8</note> enlargeth our ſteps, and gives us ſtrength that wee faint not, but ſtill helpeth us to<note n="t" place="margin">Phil. 3.14</note> 
                     <hi>preſſe toward the marke, till we obtaine the price of our high calling of God through him.</hi> And this wee ought to doe with the more care and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtneſſe, there being ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that look upon us, whom wee may encourage by our example, either in doing or ſuffering. Wee little thinke how many doe eye us in our Chriſtian walke, and what
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:1858:90"/> good wee may doe by<note n="a" place="margin">Phil. 2.15</note> 
                     <hi>hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth the light of</hi> a good example, how it may<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 9.2 1 The. 1.6, 7</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke others to mend their pace, and to runne with the more cheerefulneſſe, having ſome to lead the way before them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Section 15.</hi> How we are to ſtirre up our ſelves when our last end ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>procheth.</head>
                  <p>VVHen our laſt end approacheth, and wee lye upon our laſt bed, (if God bee ſo mercifull to us as to afford any ſtrength, eaſe, or reſpit from paine, freedome from Temptation, or to continue the uſe of our
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:1858:91"/> reaſon and memory) it is our duty to ſtirre up our ſelves, that we quit our ſelves well in the laſt act of our life: and this is done,</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 1 By a carefull prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our ſelves for our bleſſed change, and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting hence, by making our reckonings even, and expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing by all ſignes and tokens, <hi>our</hi>
                     <note n="c" place="margin">Phil. 1.12</note> 
                     <hi>deſire of being diſſolved, and to be with Chriſt.</hi> Now to ſtirre up our hope, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt expectation of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of all thoſe bleſſed promiſes of the life to come,<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>, The ſame word uſed, Rom. 8.19</note> according as the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaks of himſelf, <hi>Phi.</hi> 1.20. the word uſed by him there, ſignifies to reach out ones necke in looking after ſomewhat we greatly deſire,
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:1858:91"/> and earneſtly expect to come unto us. Ask is ſaid of<note n="d" place="margin">Iudg. 5.28</note> 
                     <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſera his Mother, ſhe looked out at a window,</hi> and expecting the returne of her ſonne, <hi>ſhee cryed, Why are his Chariots ſo long a comming?</hi> So now the ſoule ſhould be looking out, and reaching forth it ſelfe, expecting that good howre when God will ſend for it. O when the immortall ſoule which hath long ſo-journed in this ſinfull fleſh, ſhall be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginne to<note n="e" place="margin">Intrepidè purgamus ad Redemptorem noſtrum Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum, intrepidè ad Patriar— charum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilium, trepi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de ad patrem noſtrum <hi>A— braham</hi> enm dies adveneris pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fie; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>amur <hi>Ambr, lib, de bono mortis,</hi>
                     </note> draw neere to the confines of eternity, there being, it may bee, but a few houres, and, as it were, but a ſtep betweene it and everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting bleſſedneſſe, and thoſe beatificall viſions, which in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely tranſcend all that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver mortall eye ſaw, as farre
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:1858:92"/> as the glory of the greateſt Princes Court doth the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Cottage, how ſhould wee beginne to <hi>lift up our heads with ioy, the</hi>
                     <note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 21.28</note> 
                     <hi>day of our</hi> finall <hi>redemption</hi> from ſinne and miſery, <hi>being ſo neare?</hi> Here indeed ſometimes, and it is but ſometimes, we have a glimpſe of heaven ſhewed us, and a ray and beame of celeſtiall joy hath beene let downe into our harts, which hath infinitely paſſed all the pleaſures of nature, but it ſtayes not long; but now thou art going to take full poſſeſſion of that glorious inheritance which hath more comforts in it than the heaven hath Starres; or there be Sands on the Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhore, how ſhould thy heart
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:1858:92"/>
                     <note n="g" place="margin">When Doctor <hi>Tailor</hi> that worthy Martyr was going to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, he ſaw a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>far off many people ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked what it meant; it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing told him it was the place where he muſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, he ſaid, thanked be God, I am e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven at home <hi>Fox, Act. &amp; Mon. vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 178.</note> leape within thee, and ſpring forth to meet thoſe approaching bleſſings?</p>
                  <p n="2">2. By<note n="h" place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratum eſt cunctis ferè mortalibus ut morituri ſub ultimum vita exitum hortationem apud ſuos re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquere ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veant. <hi>in vit. Cranmeri, p. 15</hi>
                     </note> applying our ſelves in all the wayes of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, counſell, and comfort, in regard of ſuch as are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout us; it may be a ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full wife, who ſtands beſides thee with a heart ready to burſt, to thinke of her lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of thee; it may bee children, or ſervants ſtand before thee weeping, or neere friends or kindred are with thee, who are loth to leave thee; now to ſtirre up thy ſelfe to leave ſomewhat with them, which they may remember when thou art in the duſt: That the child may ſay, I have loſt a carefull fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, theſe were my fathers
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:1858:93"/> words, and laſt charge unto me, thoſe that ſtand by may ſay, <hi>Thus did hee exhort us, thus did hee comfort us,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> did the like being neere his end, <hi>vid, Bez, in vit. Calv.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>theſe were his laſt words, thus went he to his rest.</hi> We ſhall finde it recorded of the Patriarke <hi>Iacob,</hi> that drawing neere his end, when his children came to ſee him, he ſtirred up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,<note n="i" place="margin">Gen. 48.2.9.20</note> 
                     <hi>and ſtrengthened him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe on his bed, and he bleſſed them.</hi> A worthy patterne for all parents to follow, he lay not like a logge in his bed, as many doe, but now, though of great age, and weake, yet hee raiſed up that little ſtrength which was left, and ſpent it in<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 49.23</note> leaving a bleſſing on his children; his laſt words were bleſſings.<note n="l" place="margin">Ioh. chap. 13, 14, 15, 16 17, <hi>per tot.</hi>
                     </note> Our Saviour, when hee was to
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:1858:93"/> leave this world, ſhewed his great care and love to his Diſciples, in preparing them for his departure, and leaving with them many precious counſels, comforts, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortations, by which they might be helped and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened for the time to come. Thus did the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> imitate his Maſter,<note n="m" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.12 to 15</note> 
                     <hi>Who knowing ſhortly hee was to put off his Tabernacle, he did ſtirre them up;</hi> that after his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture they might have thoſe things alwayes in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance which he had taught them. The Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> being how aged, and<note n="n" place="margin">Acts 30.18 to 35</note> know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the time of his departure was at hand, hee called for the Elders of the Church of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and leaves with
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:1858:94"/> them many excellent and weighty exhortations, they being now to ſee his face no more.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> Shewing the grounds of this duty of ſtirring up our ſelves.</head>
               <p>THus you have the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planation of thoſe two things propoſed; <hi>to wit;</hi> what it is to ſtirre up ones ſelfe; and ſecondly, about what it is mainly to bee exerciſed. Now follow ſome grounds and reaſons of the Point.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> This duty, as it is enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, &amp; commanded by God himſelfe, that we ſhould ſtir
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:1858:94"/> up our ſelves in what we do, that it be done with all our might,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as the word is.</note> with an harmonicall conſent of all parts of man, underſtanding, will, and all the faculties exiſting in the perſon of man, with the whole ſtrength; ſo it is moſt pleaſing unto God, as moſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to his nature, who is a Spirit infinitely active &amp; ſtirring, and impatient of all dulneſſe and ſluggiſhneſſe. <hi>The</hi>
                  <note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 68.17</note> 
                  <hi>Angels are his Chariots,</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 18.10</note> 
                  <hi>he rides upon a Cherube, and doth flye; he comes alſo on the wings of the wind:</hi>
                  <note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 19.1</note> 
                  <hi>he rides on a ſwift cloud,</hi> which the racke wind drives, all which ſhadow out unto us the won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull activity of his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: <hi>Who</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">Iohn 4.24</note> 
                  <hi>ſeekes therefore ſuch to worſhip him.</hi> Hence
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:1858:95"/> is <hi>David</hi> commended for his readineſſe to fulfill all the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Acts 13.22 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <note n="t" place="margin">2. Sam. 6.14</note> wils of God, for ſo it is in the Originall. Thus he dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced before the Lord with al his might; that is, with the might of his ſpirit.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> Our Saviour Chriſt, who gave himſelfe for us in the greatneſſe of his love, (<note n="u" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14</note> 
                  <hi>even of his love that paſſeth know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi>) and<note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 2.14</note> 
                  <hi>purchaſed us to be a peculiar people to himſelfe,</hi> did it to this end, <hi>that wee ſhould be zealous of good works.</hi> Zeale is an affection proper to Men, who having will, to which belongeth the choice of good, as the object of it, have two attendants theron, the Concupiſcible, and the Iraſcible part; the former moving towards the object,
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:1858:95"/> the latter encountring what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever difficulties hinder the attaining and enjoying of it;<note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 8.6, 7</note> 
                  <hi>The coles thereof are coles of fire, which have a vehement flame, which many waters can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not quench, nor floods drowne.</hi> Hence, ſuch as are Chriſts, are<note n="b" place="margin">Luke 3.16</note> baptized with fire; that is, with the holy Ghoſt, who is like fire; not onely in purging away their droſſe and corruptions, but mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly heating them, and ſtirring up ſtrong and ardent affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in them for God and his glory.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, wee ſhould put forth our ſelves in this duty, in regard of that wonderfull aptneſſe that is in the beſt to grow cold, and dull, and that inſenſibly; even as age, and
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:1858:96"/> yeares come on us and we feele it not, and as the duſt falls upon our clothes, and we perceive it not; ſo that, if one let himſelfe alone but a ſhort time, the minde will ſinke, and get downeward: wee muſt therefore ever and anon be winding it up, as we do our Clocks and Watches, and ſtill bee tending unto it by renuing our purpoſes, and<note n="c" place="margin">Pſa. 132.4, 5 Pſal. 137.5, 6</note> tasking our ſelves to all du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, that the heart may bee kept in its due height, and this muſt be done often, the heart being not in that frame in the evening as it was in the morning: As an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Muſicke, though put never ſo well in tune over night, though it reſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toucht by an externall hand,
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:1858:96"/> yet the ſtrings will fall and grow out of tune of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and thou ſhalt finde a few weekes will breed a great alteration in thee, which many moneths may not recover againe: ſuch wretched natures doe wee carry about us, which are ſuch great enemies to the worke of grace, that if wee looke not very narrowly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, a great dampe and chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhneſſe will fall upon our hearts, our prayers wil grow weaker and weaker, ſhorter and ſhorter, good purpoſes and reſolutions will quickly dye, goe out, and bee loſt in us. Happy is he that can ſay in a ſpirituall ſenſe (as it was ſaid of <hi>Moſes</hi>) that after long profeſſion of Religion,<note n="d" place="margin">Deut 34 7</note> 
                  <hi>his
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:1858:97"/> ſight is not waxed dimme, nor his Spirituall force and heat abated.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> Where the Doctrine is applyed in the ſeverall uſes of it.</head>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>1</label> THis ſhewes us that the profeſſion of Religion, and the exerciſe of it, is no dull or lazy thing, but a bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe of the greateſt inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all others in the world, unto which is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſtrength and<note n="e" place="margin">Non eſt ad magna facilis aſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; quem ſudorem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petimur cum co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amur aſco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere c lles, &amp; vertices mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium? quid ut aſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endan us ad coelum? <hi>Cyp. de diſ. &amp; hab. Virg.</hi>
                  </note> high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pitch of our affections, our moſt elevated thoughts, and the utmoſt of our ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours.</p>
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:1858:97"/>
               <p>Againe, it ſhewes how much they do deceive them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, that content them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with doing duties of Religion out of forme, and cuſtome, without theinward Principles of Faith,<note n="f" place="margin">Quodlibet agens propter amorem agit, quodcunque agit, <hi>Aq. 1.2 q. 28. art. 6</hi>
                  </note> Love, and Obedience, to ſet them a going, and to move and ſtir them forward. Amongſt theſe we may ranke,</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Papiſts, whoſe Religion cannot be but joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and uncomfortable, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting in the work done; who if they can give in ſuch a number and tale of Prayers, undergoe ſuch penance, and ſcrew up their outward De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions to ſuch a height, thinke all is wel, though the heart all this while hath not ſtirred a foot about the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:1858:98"/> nor ſo much as looked toward the body what it was a doing.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Amongſt our ſelves we may take in our ſimple ignorant people, who are full Papiſts in this; who therefore thinke they have prayed, becauſe they have bin upon their knees; heard the Sermon well, becauſe they have beene at Church, &amp;c. and ſo plod on from day to day, without any ſenſe of the evill, or comfort of the good.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Thus is the Civill man, and carnall Profeſſor decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; who though hee hath more knowledge than the other, and by the benefit of education, good example, or the light of naturall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience,
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:1858:98"/> hath more dealings with God, yet hath hee his heart as cold, ſtarke, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirring as the other; and though he applaud himſelfe in the Mediocrity of his temper, as having found out a<note n="g" place="margin">Nihil Sal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vator <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um ama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pido<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>Hieron.</hi>
                  </note> middle way to ſerve his turne, betweene ſtrictneſſe and profaneneſſe; yet is it of al others the moſt dangerous and moſt loathed by the Lord, who, being of the<note n="h" place="margin">Rev. 3.16</note> 
                  <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odecean</hi> temper, ſhall certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bee ſpued out of Gods mouth.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Thus is it with the ſubtill and cloſe hypocrites of theſe times, who, like the cold Glow-wormes of the night, ſeeme to carry more light about them, and make a greater buſtling than the
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:1858:99"/> other; yet becauſe it is with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all heat and ſweat of the minde and heart, what they doe ſhall be reckoned but as<note n="i" place="margin">Heb. 9.14</note> 
                  <hi>dead workes,</hi> which have a loathſome ſavour in the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrils of the Almighty. Thus the<note n="k" place="margin">Rev. 31</note> 
                  <hi>Angell, or Miniſter of the Church of Sardis</hi> is ſayd to <hi>have a name to live, though he was dead.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>2</label> This may bee for tryall and examination of our ſelves, what our care and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devour is in ſtirring up our ſelves in all duties and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of piety; How have we anſwered all that coſt and care of God towards us? How doe our hearts run and cleave to the Lord in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring him before all things,<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 73.26</note> ſatisfied with him alone?
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:1858:99"/> How are wee for Chriſt? ſince <hi>the ſaithfull called and choſen are with Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 12.7 &amp; 17.14</note> 
                  <hi>fighting on his ſide againſt the Dragon and his Angels,</hi> againſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt and all his Adherents; and ſince<note n="n" place="margin">Mat. 12.30</note> he <hi>that is not with Christ, is against him;</hi> and <hi>hee that gathereth not with him, ſcattereth with the Devil</hi> Our new Creation giving a new diſpoſition, whereby we riſe up on the Lords ſide, againſt whom, before,<note n="o" place="margin">Rom. 8 7</note> our wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome was enmity. Doe thou ſeriouſly weigh what anſwer thou canſt give, as in Gods preſence, without deceiving thy ſelfe, or others, unto that preſſing queſtion of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,<note n="p" place="margin">Mat. 5 47 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, What ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar thing do you?</note> 
                  <hi>What doe ye more than others?</hi> What doe you more than the carnal and profane?
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:1858:100"/> than the civill, or the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criticall profeſſor? What doe you more for God than theſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>3</label> How may this ſmite, as with a mighty ſcourge of reproofe, the very ſpirits of Gods owne people for that ſluggiſh and bed-rid diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that cleaves to our na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? How doth our won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful guiltineſſe of the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of this duty begirt, and beſiege us on every ſide? Whoſe heart may not ſmite him? Whoſe minde doth not ſecretly miſ-give him, and falls under the thought of his grievous omiſſions? Whoſe conſcience doth not tell him that hee is involved and enwrapped in this ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual drowſineſſe and Lethar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie?
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:1858:100"/> Who may not take up this heavy complaint, <hi>There is none that ſtirreth up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe?</hi> and may ſay, and I am one of them: and ſo may I ſay, that ſpeake this; and thou that heareſt this. Ah wee fooles, and ſlow of heart, we have not put forth our ſelves in any proportion anſwerable to the grace gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, or mercies received. Ah! (deare Chriſtian) hee that ſhall looke backe, and take a ſerious view of the time of his life ſince his cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and ſhall conſider what ſpeciall opportunities of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and receiving good h e hath fore-ſlowed, how cold and careleſſe hee hath bin to oppoſe, or prevent ſinne in himſelfe or others; what a
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:1858:101"/> dead heart hee hath had for the moſt part, in all the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Gods worſhip, both in his prayers to him, his prayſes of him, and his ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for him; how the bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of his compaſſions have bin lockt up from his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, whoſe good he ſhould more have tendred: his ſlack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and ſlownes in his chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian race, going moſt an end a ſnailes pace, as though hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven were notworth the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming thither: if any ſhall (I ſay) conſider his many fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, and groſſe omiſſions in althe aggravating circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of them, if the teares ſtand not in his eyes, he hath juſt cauſe to complaine of he hardneſſe of his heart. Ah if our hearts were ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:1858:101"/> with lights and tapers, what a deale of luggage and lumber would there bee found? what heaps of droſſe, of cold and ſluggiſh matter would appeare to lye dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and damping thoſe few ſparkes of heat, and little light yet remaining in us? Good Lord! how full are we of our ſelves, and of the world? what ſtrange luſts and paſſions lye yet unmor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified in us? which keepe downe our minds that wee cannot lift them up to divine and ſpirituall things: May it not be ſaid in a ſpirituall ſenſe of moſt of our hearts and houſes, as the<note n="q" place="margin">Iſa. 47.14</note> Prophet ſpeakes, <hi>there is not a cole to warme it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>4</label> How ſhould this humble
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:1858:102"/> and aſhame us? how ſhould wee bewaile this wretched luskiſhneſſe and ſluggiſhnes of our ſpirits, this indiſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this unactiveneſſe and unzealouſneſſe, if it were poſſible, with teares of blood? The godly are wont to eſteeme of life, not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that they find in their body, but their ſoule; when that wants a heavenly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to ſpirituall things, they lament over it as a dead ſoule, ſince herein ſtands the life of it, to be ſtirring and active in our duties of love and obedience.<note n="r" place="margin">Iſa. 38.15<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.16.</note> 
                  <hi>O Lord, by theſe things men live, and in all theſe things is the life of my ſpirit,</hi> ſaith that good King <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> Let us view our ſelves in the ſeverall relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:1858:102"/> wee ſtand towards o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, whether Magiſtrate, Miniſter, Parent, Maſter of a Family, Friend or Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, &amp;c. and then let us but ſtand a while and think what good might have beene done, which now hath been fore-ſlowed in our owne hearts, in our families, and abroad: if in our firſt ſetting out in our Chriſtian race wee had thus beſtirred our ſelves; now that time is paſt and gone, and ſpilt like water on the ground, which can no more bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered up againe! What prayers and Sermons have beene loſt, &amp;c. what ſinne and evill might have beene avoyded, what ſinne might have beene reſtrained by us,
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:1858:103"/> the guilt of which now ſtickes upon us. But more eſpecially ſhould it abaſe us, and throw us downe in our ſelves, and make us bluſh within our ſelves, that wee have bin ſo vilely wanting to the Lord and his grace, that we have not ſtirred up our ſelves according to the grace given, and abilities be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon us; in that wee have not done that which we might have done, and was in our power to do, both in regard of reſiſting ſins and temptations, and perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming duties of piety and mercy. <note place="margin">Whether a man may do more then he doth with that ability which he hath?</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Queſt. </seg>
                  </label> But here it may be deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, Whether a man may doe more than he doth with that ability which he hath?</p>
               <pb n="183" facs="tcp:1858:103"/>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> For the anſwering of this queſtion, I ſhall lay downe theſe ſeverall poſitions:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it is granted that an unregenerate man can do no good Spirituall without grace;<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mat. 12.33</note> 
                  <hi>the tree muſt be good before the fruit can be good:</hi> As<note n="t" place="margin">Iohn 15.4.</note> 
                  <hi>the branch beareth not fruit but in the Vine, Iohn</hi> 15.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, Yet a naturall man may doe more then he doth, towards the attainment of a better ſtate, and to the good of other men, they might uſe meanes, as Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, reading, prayer, as it is an outward action, ſo giving to the poore, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, a regenerate Chriſtian, as in his firſt rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, he is only paſſive, God infuſing new habits of
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:1858:104"/> grace, new qualities into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very faculty: ſo after rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration hee cannot doe<note n="u" place="margin">Rom. 7.15. Gal. 5.17.</note> all the good he would, nor when he would, nor as hee would.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, A regenerate Chriſtian after grace recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, ſtandeth in need not onely of generall ayd,<note n="*" place="margin">It is Gods free grace, his volunta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry influence which habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuateth and fitteth al our faculties, which ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate thus unto a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly being, which gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us both the ſtrength and firſt act, whereby we are qualified to work, and which con. curreth with us <hi>in astu ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cundo,</hi> to all thoſe works which we ſet ourſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout. As an inſtrument, even when it hath an edge cutteth nothing till it be aſſiſted and moved by the hand of the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer: ſo a Chriſtian, when he hath a will and an habituall fitneſſe to worke, yet is able to doe nothing without a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant ſupply and aſſiſtance and eoncomitancy of the grace of Chriſt, exciting, moving, and applying that habituall power unto particular Actions. <hi>E. R.</hi>
                  </note> but of ſupply of new grace, to put forth every ſpirituall act of grace; partly for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king out of his owne ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and partly for the more ſpirituall and lively perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance and accompliſhment of the worke it ſelfe. Hee ſtandeth in need of,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Preparing grace, that
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:1858:104"/> whereby God prepared the heart of <hi>Titus</hi> to receive <hi>Pauls</hi> exhortation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.17. By this grace the hearts of Gods people are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to pray, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Exciting, or awake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, or quickning grace: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.4. in the latter end of the verſe, <hi>Hee wakeneth mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by morning, hee wakeneth my eare to heare as the learned.</hi> So, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 143.11.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Aſſiſting and ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning grace, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Enlarging grace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.32.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Directing grace, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.5.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Protecting, or preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving grace, keeping off pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing interruptions, <hi>Eſay</hi> 27.3.</p>
               <p n="7">
                  <pb n="186" facs="tcp:1858:105"/>7. Perfecting grace, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.10.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, Though a rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate Chriſtian cannot by his owne abilities excite, or prepare, or enlarge his owne heart to any Spirituall duty, yet by the grace he hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, he may, and ought to uſe the meanes which God hath appointed for the ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring up of the heart towards God: for,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Hee may walke in a conſcionable care not to live in any knowne ſinne, or after the fleſh; for to live after the fleſh, deadeth and dulleth the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.13.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He may abſtaine from the conſtant, abundant uſe of ſenſuall comforts; for ſuch (though lawfull) will ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:1858:105"/> choake the heart of a Chriſtian, as they did <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Hee may diligently uſe the holy Ordinances of God, eſpecially the hearing of the Word where it is Preached with power; in the uſe whereof, a regenerate Chriſtian, by grace received, exceedeth a naturall man, in that a naturall man can onely heare, but not upon a right ground, nor for a right end; but a regenerate Chriſtian, by grace received, may heare in obedience to Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, and for his edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſeeking and waiting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God for a bleſſing, <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He may diſcerne the dulneſſe and deadneſſe of his
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:1858:106"/> owne heart to all ſpirituall duties, and may<note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 63.17</note> complaine thereof unto God in prayer, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 63.17.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, for want of the uſe of theſe means he may juſtly be ſaid <hi>not to prepare his owne heart,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12.14. <hi>not to ſtir up himſelfe to take hold of God,</hi> as in the Text: and ſo therby to<note n="x" place="margin">Ephe. 4.30</note> 
                  <hi>grieve the holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God,</hi>
                  <note n="y" place="margin">2 Cor. 6.1</note> and <hi>to receive the grace of God in vaine,</hi> and therfore may juſtly be repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved hereof, and complained of, as in the Text. Beſides this, the conſtant experience of all the children of God wil beare them witneſſe, that there be no ſinnes that lye more heavy upon them, or under which they doe more deepely grone and mourne,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:1858:106"/> than their walking unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of thoſe precious mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and graces they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived,<note n="z" place="margin">Verum, heu mihi, ſtudium ellud meum et zelus (ſi hoc nomine dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt) adeo remiſſus &amp; languidus fuit ut innu mera mihi ad mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus meum preclarè fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum defu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſſe fatear <hi>In Teſt. Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vini in vita ipſis, p. 102</hi> Queſt.</note> neither growing up in them to that ſtrength, nor imploying them to that fruitfulneſſe they might have attained unto.</p>
               <p>But why is it a ſinne not to ſtir up our ſelves to holy duties, ſince exciting grace is Gods worke alone, and hee muſt renew it every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, elſe the worke wil not be done, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 50.4.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>1</label> 
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Becauſe it is by reaſon of our ſinne that God doth not ſtir us up: as,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Our narrowneſſe of heart and mouth in prayer, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.10. Aske liberally and have liberally: prayers are<note n="a" place="margin">2 King. 13.17, 18, 19.</note> like arrowes of Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance,
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:1858:107"/> which would be mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplied and enlarged.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Our heedleſneſſe in the uſe of the Ordinances, <hi>Luk.</hi> 8.18.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Unfruitfulneſſe in the uſe of grace received, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.29.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Unbeleefe, <hi>Mat.</hi> 14.31. elſe renewing our waiting on the Lord for his help and grace, would renew our ſtrength, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40.31.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee how ſtill the fault<note n="b" place="margin">Rectè homo corripitur que precepta non implet quia exetus negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia eſt quod gratiam non habet per quam poſſit ſervare man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>data. <hi>Th. Aq. queſt. diſp. 24. art. 14</hi>
                  </note> returnes upon our ſelves, how we cannot ſtand before this truth, but muſt lye downe as condemned of our ſelves, and guilty of this evill, that we have not ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up our ſelves to doe that which was in our power to have done, that good (I ſay)
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:1858:107"/> which wee ought and might have done.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Vſe </seg>5</label> What remaines now but that I ſhould call upon you, and my ſelfe, with all the ſtrength of exhortation I may, (and the Lord grant it may be effectuall to us all) that wee ſet about this ſo needfull a Chriſtian duty, and that if it be poſſible we might bee drawne off from our dregs and lees, to get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove our ſelves, and to bee heightned in our deſires, and practice of all Chriſtian duties, to doe them in a more lively, active, and ſtirring manner: this being like oyle to the wheeles, and as wind to the ſayles that ſets all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going; this indeed is all in all, for what are all our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices,
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:1858:108"/> but ſapleſſe, liveleſſe, and loathſome things with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this?</p>
               <p>And firſt I would bend my ſpeech to ſuch as formerly have bin more forward and ſtirring-hearted, but now are growne more remiſſe and ſpirit-leſſe: I would ſpeake to ſuch, in the Name of God, as the Lord ſpeakes by the Prophet to his people,<note n="c" place="margin">Ier. 2.5</note> 
                  <hi>What iniquity have your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers found in mee, that they are gone from mee?</hi> What e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill have you found in Gods wayes, that you are growne weary of them? Speake, in the preſence of God, what evill have you found in prayer, that you grow ſo ſlacke in it? You were wont you could have gone to
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:1858:108"/> the Lord with much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>largement, and, it may bee, with many teares;<note n="d" place="margin">Pſa. 45.1</note> 
                  <hi>your tongue was as the pen of a ready Writer;</hi> why are you now ſo narrow-hearted? Why doe you ſo fore-ſlow the duty?<note place="margin">Siccine puta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus oraſſe <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam?</hi> Sic <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nielem</hi> inter Leones? Sic latr nem in cruces? Hier. <hi>ſpeaking thereof cold prayers.</hi>
                  </note> and make ſo many excuſes? and are ſo loth to come into Gods preſence? neither is there that ſtrugling againſt this woful diſpoſition as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly. What evill have you found in Gods word? the time was when you went with much joy to Gods houſe, and you loved the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble above al books, and now it can lie a day, &amp; ſometimes a weeke, and you never looke into it?<note n="e" place="margin">Iob 15.11</note> 
                  <hi>Are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he conſolations of God ſmall with you?</hi> are the counſels and exhortations of
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:1858:109"/> the Scriptures grown weake? Are the Promiſes of God more dry and withered? Is not God ſtill a hearer of praiers? or is his arme ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned that it cannot ſave? God forbid! But doth not the fault lye in yourſelfe, unto whom the world, and other ſinfull diſtempers have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the relliſh and taſte of theſe Divine counſels and comforts? What evill have you found in the ſocietie of Gods people? of whoſe grace and goodneſſe you cannot bee but well perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; why are you ſo ſtrange unto them? the time hath bin when you have prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them before all others, and choſe them for the one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly companions of your life,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:1858:109"/> you could have opened your mouth to the edification of others, but now you are like a curſt Cowe that will not give downe her milke; you can now like well enough of carnall ſpeech, and worldly companie, and can ſort your ſelfe with ſuch of whoſe happineſſe you have no per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion. Speake, is not this your caſe? are you not blame-worthy? why then be grieved, and ſigh within your ſelfe: and<note n="f" place="margin">Rev. 2.4, 5</note> 
                  <hi>Remember from whence thou art fallen, and repent and doe thy first workes.</hi> Let our Saviours counſell come ſeaſonably to thee,<note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 3.2</note> 
                  <hi>Be watchfull to ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the things which remaine which are ready to dye</hi> reſt not in this unprofitable and
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:1858:110"/> uncomfortable condition, till thou find thy ſpirit to revive, and thy care of better things to flouriſh, and ſpring againe in thee:<note n="h" place="margin">Heb. 12.12 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Lift up thy hands that hang downe, and the fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knees, leſt that which bee lame be turned out of the way.</hi> Labour to recover thy for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer ſtrength and ſtation; and therefore to cheriſh and blow up that fire which yet remaines hid under the aſhes<note n="i" place="margin">2 Iohn 8</note> 
                  <hi>that thou loſe not that which thou hest wrought, but mayest receive a full reward.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But leſt any be diſcoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,<note place="margin">Cauti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n.</note> wee are to know, that this dulneſſe and unſtirring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart, may proceed ſometime from</p>
               <p n="1">1. Weakneſſe, faintneſſe, and feeblenes of body, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:1858:110"/> it beinregard of preſent ſickneſſe, indiſpoſition to health, age, or other bodily infirmities, in which caſe a good Chriſtian may be fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in performance of duties the minde moſt an end fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing the preſent temper of the body.</p>
               <p n="2">2. It may proceed from melancholy diſtempers with which the minde may be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-growne.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Or the party may lye under ſome violent tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Satan, or diſtreſſe of conſcience, which may ſtrangely, for the time, make one dull, mopiſh, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Or it may proceed from ſpirituall deſertion, when the ſenſe of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour,
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:1858:111"/> love and wonted pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence may be departed from him for a time.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Or the outward meanes of the Word may be taken from them, either wholly, or it may be much ecclipſed, which formerly they en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in more plentie and power.</p>
               <p>Theſe, and many ſuch like, may bring a dulneſſe upon the hart in Duties; but if thy weariſomneſſe in duties, and thy decayings in good ariſe from none of theſe, but that it hath rooting and foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in thy owne corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and is cheriſhed and fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented by the <hi>lusts of other things,</hi> thoumuſt take it home to thy ſelfe, and know thy caſe is ſo much the worſe,
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:1858:111"/> and that thou art laden with the more guilt, by how much thou art left without excuſe, God having done ſo well for thee, and thou ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo<note n="k" place="margin">Deut. 32.6</note> ill requited him.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, this exhortation is to be ſet home upon every one that feares the name of God, be they poore or rich, noble or meane, learned or unlearned, young or old, all need it, and therefore all may harken to it; for all to kindle and quicken up our ſelves, to ſharpen and ſet an edge upon our ſelves, to rouze up our ſelves, to preſſe forward and goe an end with all our might, in all our duties. O what is worthy our care, paines and travell if this be not, to have our ſpirits quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:1858:112"/> and enlivened with ſtronger incitations to what is required of us, to tugge and toyle, to labor &amp;<note n="l" place="margin">Non ad ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borem tantum ſed ad ſudore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</note> ſweat in this worke, breaking through all difficulties, and bearing up againſt all oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions. As the Cocke claps his wings to ſtirre up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to crowe, and as a fire-brand borne in the wind is the<note n="m" place="margin">See <hi>Davids</hi> anſwer when <hi>Michall</hi> his wife mocked him, 2 S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 20 21, 22, 23</note> more enkindled; and as <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſtirred up his ſtrength, when it was told him the <hi>Philistims</hi> were up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him. As there was more in <hi>Sampſon</hi> than in another man, ſo is there in every true Chriſtian, who being in co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant with God, and having his vowes upon him, he goes forth in the ſtrength of theſe and ſo long as he<note n="n" place="margin">Judg. 6 14</note> 
                  <hi>goes forth
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:1858:112"/> in this might,</hi> and cleaves to him that is the ſtrength of Iſrael, ſo long no ſinne ſhall maſter him, nor duty be too hard for him; otherwiſe <hi>hee ſhall bee weake, and as another man.</hi> Hence it is that <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſaith,<note n="o" place="margin">Pro. 15 24</note> 
                  <hi>The way of life is above to the wiſe.</hi> The godly man goeth an higher way than his neighbour, even in the common buſineſſes of this life, even of his ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry calling, becauſe they are done in<note n="p" place="margin">Gal. 2.20 Rom. 14.23</note> faith and<note n="q" place="margin">Deut. 5.29</note> obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: much more when hee draweth neere to God in more immediate duties of his worſhip, as when we are to praiſe him, or ſtand for him This is that which p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> s the difference, even the hea t ſtirred and moved with theſe
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:1858:113"/> principles, which being wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in every naturall man, the heart muſt needs ſinke, and flagge in his performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. O then that there were ſuch an heart in us as to goe this higher way, to get a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the ordinary ſort, even like the Aegles of heaven, who delight themſelves in their high flying, and when they are fartheſt from the earth: ſo to get above earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, and earthly things, to be as the flame, which, the higher it riſeth, the purer it is; ſo ſtill to bee aſpiring in our thoughts, deſires and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours, and to get them up to ſuch a pitch,<note place="margin">Prov. 4.18</note> by which they might bee freed from their dregs and droſſe.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing the ſtrength
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:1858:113"/> of our minds is the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious thing wee have, wee ſhould reſerve this for the moſt excellent duties and buſineſſes, and beſtow it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. Thus ſhal we make<note n="ſ" place="margin">Fides auget aetatem. <hi>Amb</hi>
                  </note> a ſhort life a long one, and thus ſhalt thou live more in a day, than another doth in ſeven yeares, or in all his time: for it is not to be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned a life which is meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with dayes and yeares; but that which is<note n="t" place="margin">In brevi vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſpatio tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a virtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum multa complevit. <hi>Hieron. Ep. ad Fu.</hi>
                  </note> filled with good Actions, with fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent prayers, with walking in an awfull feare of God, with denying thy ſelfe, and mortifying, thy luſts, with bearing afflictions patiently, with giving good example unto others, to helpe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed and afflicted, to ſtand
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:1858:114"/> on Gods ſide, oppoſing the ſinnes and evils of the times, &amp;c this is truly to live; theſe are the moſt noble actions of life, and theſe are the moſt excellent iſſues and produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the mind and ſoule</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> Shewing ſome motives unto this duty of ſtirring up our ſelves.</head>
               <p>NOw that wee might be farther moved and ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up hereunto (for God knowes that great is our dul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and ſloware our appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſions of theſe things) let us conſider in the generall how wee are commanded<note n="u" place="margin">Cor. 11.3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor 14.12</note> 
                  <hi>earneſtly to covet the beſt gifts</hi>
                  <pb n="205" facs="tcp:1858:114"/> and * <hi>to ſtudy that we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell;</hi> and that it is honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to be<note n="x" place="margin">2 Cor. 9.2</note> leaders in good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to be preſidents of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety, provoking others; and that if this ſtirringneſſe of heart bee wanting, all goes but heavily forward. As the<note n="y" place="margin">Exo. 14.25</note> Aegyptians, who, when their wheeles were taken off, drave their Chariots but heavily. But more ſpecially there be three things which I would offer to your conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration to move to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, looke a while, and ſee what a ſtirring and buſie world it is,<note place="margin">Conſider what a ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring world it is.</note> how mightily men are put forward, and ſet a going in their ſeverall wayes, according to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall projects they drive,
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:1858:115"/> and thoſe inward principles by which they worke, and by which they walke. The world is as a great Ant, or Emit-hill, where there are multitudes of thoſe buſie creatures, carrying and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carrying ſtrawes, ſtubble, or other ſuch luggage, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one buſie in doing ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and intent to adde, and bring to the heape: So in this world there is a mighty and general buſineſſe, an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt trudging about, a conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued ſollicitouſneſſe, plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and working upon the face of the earth. See it in a few inſtances:</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Time-ſerver is buſie to fit his ſailes to every wind, marks what is in grace and faſhion with the Times,
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:1858:115"/> obſerves the Motions of great ones, and ſtudies how he may pleaſe the moſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The deepe and clung-headed Politician, who dwels many times the next doore to Atheiſme, is buſie in wheeling about his owne ends, is darke in his wayes, and uſually, like a Boat-man, lookes one way, and rowes another.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Ambitious man puts on <hi>Abſolons</hi> behaviour, is buſie in ſeeking applauſe and reſpect and how he may be carried aloft, as a feather, upon the breath of men.</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Voluptuous man is buſie to draw out the quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſence of all ſinnes and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities; to ſucke the ſweet out of them, to array him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:1858:116"/> like a childe of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, and to have his part in all the pleaſures of nature.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The worldling is bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie in telling his money, ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting up his accounts, loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in his Almanacke, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring for a purchaſe, <hi>enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging his barnes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 12.18.</note> alwayes plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting how hee may get or ſave. The Papiſts are buſie to advance the Catholicke cauſe, as they call it, to make Proſelytes; buſie they are in their Devotions, as the<note n="z" place="margin">Ier. 7.18</note> Prophet ſpeakes, <hi>The Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren gather wood and the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers kindle the fire &amp; the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men knead their dough to make cakes to the Queene of heaven.</hi> The Devill is buſie,<note n="a" place="margin">Iob 1.7</note> 
                  <hi>going to and fro in the earth,</hi> doing miſchiefe, murdering ſoules,
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:1858:116"/> and filling Hell. All theſe, and many others, are driven with great force upon their ſeverall wayes, and are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied in them. Thus it is with the men of this world,<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 17.14</note> 
                  <hi>who have their prrtion in this life.</hi> And how ſhould this fire us, and put life and ſpirit into us, who ſerve a better maſter, and have better work to doe?<note n="c" place="margin">Turp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> eſt impios diabol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> tam ſtrenué ſervire nos Chriſto pro ſanguinis pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio nihil re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendere. <hi>Cyp. lib. de opere et ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſy.</hi>
                  </note> Why ſhould not we do more for God and his honor, than any in the world ſhould doe for themſelves, or to promote Satans king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. Let us reſolve there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with the Prophet<note n="d" place="margin">Mich. 4.5</note> 
                  <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cah, All people</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>will walke every one in the Name of his Grd,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 10.12</note> 
                  <hi>and we will walke in the Name of the Lord our God for ever and ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="210" facs="tcp:1858:117"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, let it move us to conſider how our bleſſed Savior,<note place="margin">Looke upon our Saviour, how he ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our Salvation.</note> in the great buſineſſe of our Salvation, ſtirred up himſelfe, and put forth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to his<note n="e" place="margin">Heb. 7.25. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>uttermoſt</hi> for us; he ſtirred up all his ſtrength, left nothing undone, bare as much as hee could beare,<note n="f" place="margin">Phil 2.7. <hi>Scipſum ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manivis.</hi>
                  </note> went as low as he could go, downe to the grave, even to hell it ſelfe in paines and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh of Spirit, did what poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly he could doe, which ſhould fill us with ſtrong deſires, and endevours, to enforce our ſelves to our uttermoſt, for ſo<note n="g" place="margin">Quid nos pro Domino tam b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>no fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere conveniet cum ille pro malis Servis tan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a ſeceret? <hi>Salv.</hi>
                  </note> kinde a Redeemer as we have found him to be, to love his perſon, to prize his merits, to obey his will, to delight in his Ordinances, to love his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:1858:117"/> to doe what wee may to advance his honour and ſervice, to<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 3.15</note> tread hard up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Divels head, and to be profeſſed enemies to his kingdome all our dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Laſtly, this ſtirringneſſe of heart,<note place="margin">The certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the reward.</note> as it is accompani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with much ſweet peace, and inward comfort, and reſt of heart; and as it brings a good report, and eſteeme in the Churches of Chriſt; cauſing one Chriſtian (of what degree, calling, and condition ſoever hee be) to excell another, and appeare higher, even as <hi>Saul</hi> did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the people: ſo it is attended with certainty and fulneſſe of reward, and that according to the quality of our worke; as there hath bin
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:1858:118"/> more grace in it, more reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, zeale, fervency, more faith and reſting upon God; ſo ſhall the<note n="h" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.7, 8</note> reward be more plenteous and abundant. The more faithfull ſervice wee have done, the more welcome ſhall wee bee to him when hee cals for us; As a faithfull Embaſſadour is welcomed home by his Prince; and as a Factor, that hath done his maſter good ſervice in a farre Countrey, is gladly received by him. O when the faithfull ſoule, being carried on Angels wings, ſhall firſt ſet footing on the glorious pavement of heaven, and the Lord ſhall ſay, Welcome my deare and faithfull ſervant, thou haſt beene a good ſervant unto
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:1858:118"/> me,<note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 25.23</note> 
                  <hi>Enter into the ioy of thy Lord;</hi> this ſpeech ſhall bee of more infinite refreſhing, then if ten thouſand worlds, and the glory of them, had beene given unto it; for what could bee ſpoken more by the Creator? what could be deſired more by the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? This their faithful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe alſo, with how much the more ſtirringneſſe and advantage to the Lords ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour it hath beene managed and diſcharged, by ſo much the<note n="k" place="margin">Rev. 3.21</note> neerer in place it brings us to the Lord; As <hi>Davids</hi> Worthies were admitted to have the neareſt place about his perſon. How many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands are there of Saints at this day,<note n="l" place="margin">Rev. 7.9.14 15.</note> 
                  <hi>ſtanding before the Throne of God, with Palmes in
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:1858:119"/> their hands, and Crownes on their heads,</hi> who in this world have beene the Lords Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, who have fought his battels, and lifted up his Name to their uttermoſt. Speake, O ye bleſſed ſoules departed, whether this bee not your glory and your joy that you have had your harts ſtirred for the Lord; and if you were upon the earth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, whether you would not doe, if it were poſſible, a thouſand times more for him, that for ſuch weake ſervices, ſuch poore and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect performances, hath rewarded you with the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours and joyes of eternitie.<note n="m" place="margin">Rev. 15<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3</note> 
                  <hi>O who would not feare and ſerve thee, O Lord, thou King of Saints, &amp; glorifie thy name?</hi>
                  <pb n="215" facs="tcp:1858:119"/> who makeſt all thy ſervants<note n="n" place="margin">Rev. 1.6</note> Kings, and affordeſt them everlaſting Communion with thy ſelfe! It matters not (deare brethren) what wee are in this world, how ſhunned, deſpiſed, and<note n="o" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.13</note> 
                  <hi>made the off-ſcouring of all things;</hi> nay, though every one that meets us ſhould ſpit in our faces, revile, and trample up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, if by this meanes any honour might redound to the Name of the Lord; it is enough for us to bee happy when wee dye, and to be ſet ſafe over that<note n="p" place="margin">Luk. 16.26</note> gulfe that parts Hell &amp; Heaven, and to<note n="q" place="margin">Iob 33, 26</note> 
                  <hi>ſee the face of God with ioy</hi> to all eternity. O Eternity! Eternity! bleſſed Eternity! this makes abundant amends for all, though wee ſhould
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:1858:120"/> live here thouſands of yeers, and in them all doe and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer<note n="r" place="margin">
                     <hi>Fredericke Danvile,</hi> and <hi>Francis Re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bezies</hi> after they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned from the Torture to their fel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lowes in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, reioyced together, &amp; comforted themſelves with the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation of the life to come, and contempt of this world, ſinging Pſalmes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till it was day. <hi>Eox. Act. &amp; Mon vol.</hi> 2. <hi>p.</hi> 160.</note> hard things! How ſhould this fill our hearts with great thoughts, our hands with all advantages? how ſhould wee with great courage goe forth to meet al opportunities? What a ſpur ſhould this put upon all our endevours? How ſhould we thinke our ſelves happy that ever we were borne, that the Lord hath done us this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as to put us into his ſervice? and that hee hath conferred upon ſinners and poore wormes, ſuch as thou and I are,<note n="ſ" place="margin">1 Cor. 2.9</note> 
                  <hi>Such things as nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther eye hath ſeene, eare hath heard, nor have at any time en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tredento the heart of man to conceive.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="217" facs="tcp:1858:120"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> Shewing ſome Meanes to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a ſtirring heart in duties.</head>
               <p>NOw for our further help and light in ſo needfull a point, I would lay downe ſome few helps and meanes by which we might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter attaine unto this ſtirring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of heart:</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, we ſhould endevor the removing of al thoſe lets and hindrances,<note place="margin">The remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of all thoſe impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments which damp and dead the heart.</note> which doe any way dampe and dead the heart, keepe it under, and lay bolts and fetters upon it. Such are,</p>
               <p n="1">1. Idleneſſe, ſlothfulneſſe, and careleſſe miſ-ſpending
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:1858:121"/> our time, incogitancy, let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the mind drive, as a Boat or Ship that hath none to guide it, but it floats up and downe uncertainely; ſo li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving without a calling, and the like.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Barrenneſſe, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fruitfulneſſe in our Chriſtian courſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Luſts, and paſſions, and ſuch like ſinfull diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers, which are the ſickneſſes of the ſoule, and keepe it in a low and weake eſtate.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Unneceſſary ſadneſſe, and unchecrefulneſſe.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Vaine feares of what may befall us in regard of our Chriſtian profeſſion.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The diſſwaſion of worldlymen, carnal friends, and kindred, which ſay,
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:1858:121"/> Why cannot you content your ſelfe to doe as others doe,<note place="margin">Vulgar ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches againſt the earneſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. profeſſion of Religion.</note> but you muſt make all the Towne and Countrey to talk of you, in being ſo ſtrict and preciſe, in running after Sermons, and in ſaying as many praiers as would ſerve two or three beſides, there is a reaſon in all things, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough is enough. Thus our Saviours kindred dealt with him, who ſeeing him won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull earneſt, and painfull in Preaching to the people, came to lay hold of him, thinking he had bin<note n="t" place="margin">Mark. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 20 21.</note> 
                  <hi>beſides himſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. Worldly cares, and multitude of worldly buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, which<note n="u" place="margin">Mat. 13.22</note> 
                  <hi>choakes the heart.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Sinfull pleaſures, too
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:1858:122"/> much carnall mirth, or abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of lawfull things, which mightily<note n="*" place="margin">Anima di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſa fit mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</note> weaken, intene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and emaſculate the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, and draw out the vigour and vivacity of it.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Conſorting much with Civil and Carnal company, theſe are as a continuall dropping, which inſenſibly cooles the lively operations of the Soule: A good man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſuch, is like a ſheepe amongſt the briars, he will come away a loſer, do what he can.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Reſting in thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition, contenting thy ſelfe with the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings of Grace, and with that meaſure thou haſt.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Diſcouragements in thy ſelfe at thy owne weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:1858:122"/> and inabilities for want of parts and gifts. For this God was angry with <hi>Moſes,</hi> who pleaded his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ability to goe on Gods er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand: conſider what the Lord ſaid to him,<note n="x" place="margin">Exo. 44.10</note> 
                  <hi>Who hath made mans mouth? or who ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the dumbe or deafe? or ſeeing or blind? have not I the Lord?</hi> Who hath given thee that which thou haſt? Who can increaſe it? Who alſo will expect no more then he gives.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, ſeeke this of God by earneſt prayer,<note place="margin">Earneſt prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to God. Iam. 1.19</note> 
                  <hi>from whom comes every good and perfect gift.</hi> Let thy heart follow the Lord with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant requeſts, leave him not till hee anſwer thee in this great ſuit of giving thee
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:1858:123"/> a ſtirring heart. <hi>Iabez,</hi> in the<note n="y" place="margin">1 Chr. 4.10</note> firſt of the <hi>Chronicles,</hi> makes this prayer to God, ſaying, <hi>O that thou wouldst bleſſe mee indeed, and enlarge my coaſt! and God granted him that which he requested:</hi> So doe thou ſay, O that thou wouldſt bleſſe me indeed, and enlarge my heart. This is a bleſſing <hi>indeed,</hi> if God would bee ſo gracious to thee as to grant thy requeſt. Thus<note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 143.11 &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0.11</note> 
                  <hi>David</hi> often prayeth, that <hi>God would quicken him,</hi> and <hi>unite his hart to feare the Name of God.</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Cant. 1.4</note> 
                  <hi>Draw me</hi> (ſaith the Church in the <hi>Canticles) and wee will runne after thee.</hi> Theſe are the breathings of a faithfull ſoule, and thus ſhouldſt thou doe: if thou hadſt but one requeſt to make, next to the
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:1858:123"/> ſalvation of thy ſoule, this, O this ſhould bee it, That God would give thee a ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring heart: for without this, heaven it ſelfe would not be heaven; and with this, a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry dungeon would ſeeme a corner of heaven. In all thy prayers therefore, put up one petition for this, that God would keepe this Holy fire upon the hearth of thy heart all thy dayes.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, we muſt renew our<note n="b" place="margin">Pſ 119.116</note> purpoſes and promiſes often,<note place="margin">Often to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes.</note> wee muſt lay more bonds and engagements up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our ſelves, more Vowes and Reſolutions,<note n="c" place="margin">Pſ. 132.2.8 Pſa. 137, 5, 6</note> and charge our ſelves with them, and to doe it ſolemnly with Prayer and Faſting if need require, to bind our ſelves, the more
<pb n="224" facs="tcp:1858:124"/> ſtrongly to our duties: even that wee will ſtand on the Lords ſide, and give up our ſelves more for the publike good; and for this end wee ſhould often commune and reaſon with our owne harts, chiding and reproaching our ſelves for our dulneſſe, and dejection of Spirit. <hi>Why art thou caſt down, O my ſoule</hi> (ſaith<note n="d" place="margin">Pſa. 42.5, 6</note> 
                  <hi>David;</hi>) As if hee ſhould have ſaid, O my God, I doe lye downe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrowne in the ſtrength of my minde, and I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed of my ſelfe for it: <hi>My ſoule hope thou in God, I will yet praiſe him</hi> more, I will remember him, and all his promiſes and mercies, and cleave unto them with more faith, and greater con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:1858:124"/> than ever yet I have done.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, wee ſhould of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten ſet before us the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Gods Saints and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants,<note place="margin">To ſet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us the examples of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, who have excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this way</note> who have exceeded the common meaſure in their zeale and earneſtneſſe. As the Apoſtle ſaith of the<note n="e" place="margin">1 Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.7 2 Theſ. 1.3, 4</note> 
                  <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> That <hi>they were patternes to all them which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved in Macedonia and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaia,</hi> and propounds them in their rare faith and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence with glorying.<note n="f" place="margin">Luk. 7.44</note> 
                  <hi>Seest thou this Woman</hi> (ſaith our Saviour to <hi>Simon) compare</hi> her love to mee with thine, and bee aſhamed. So alſo let us looke upon ſuch who are now living, who excell in this grace; prize them highly, rejoyce in their ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety,
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:1858:125"/> reſort unto them as to the<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 16.2</note> moſt <hi>excellent upon the earth.</hi> When wee want fire, wee uſe to goe to our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and to light our Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle at anothers flame. Seeke them out, though it coſt thee much travell and paines, they will abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly recompence all thy la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour.<note n="h" place="margin">Luk. 24.32</note> 
                  <hi>Did not our hearts burne within us,</hi> ſay the two Diſciples when they travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led together, and talked with our Saviour. O the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints! what a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing is folded up in it, and goes along with it! How doe the ſparks flye abroad? and how are our cold and dull hearts quickned and enflamed thereby? How doe Gods ſervants many
<pb n="227" facs="tcp:1858:125"/> times part from each other, bleſſing God in their hearts, that ever they ſaw the faces, or heard the voyces each of other, having got ſuch cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and ſtrength one by an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Laſtly, the carefull and frequent exerciſe of that grace we have in any kinde,<note place="margin">The fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of that grace we have.</note> helpes much to ſtirre up the heart. Every act intends the habit, and the more the acts of grace are iterated and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated, the more the grace is intended and enlarged, the more ſpreading, ſtrong, and active it growes. The more wee lay forth our ſelves, dreſſe, and tend to every grace and gift beſtowed, the greater is the increaſe and fruit of them.<note place="margin">Simile.</note> As it is in a
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:1858:126"/> tree planted, and plaſhed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a wall, the more it is ſpread, and laied forth in the branches, even to the leaſt twigge, the more warmth and vigour it gets from the Sun-beames, and the more fruit it beareth. Thus when every grace is exerciſed, and put to the beſt uſe and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, it muſt needs make a ſtirring and a fruitful Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian. And as men get warmth into their hands by rubbing them, and as the wax is made fit for the ſeale by chafing it; ſo<note n="i" place="margin">Quomodo ſine exercitio doctrinae, aut ſine uſu profe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus? Res om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis proprius ac domeſticis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercitiis auge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. <hi>Amb. offic. 1. cap. 5.</hi>
                  </note> exerciſe of grace helpes to warme and kindle the heart, and makes it fit for many Divine and heavenly impreſſions to bee put upon it. Thus fervent prayer kindles the heart, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth
<pb n="229" facs="tcp:1858:126"/> that grace by the often exerciſe of it, ſtirres up other graces in us, and ſhakes off all heavineſſe and drowſineſſe of ſoule.<note n="k" place="margin">Exo. 24.39</note> When <hi>Moſes</hi> had beene long with God in the holy Mount, there was a brightneſſe and ſhining put upon his face. So our converſing much with God by prayer puts a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter light, and brightneſſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſoule.</p>
               <p>Thus he that edifies ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, edifies himſelfe, and whilſt he is imparting what grace hee hath to others, it growes in his owne heart, as the<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 14.19.20.</note> bread did in the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples hands, whilſt they were diſtributing it to the poore hungry people. The more alſo wee put forth the
<pb n="228" facs="tcp:1858:127"/> fruits of Chriſtian love to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards others? the more loving it makes us; by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving we become more libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, and by ſhewing mercy on the diſtreſſed, more pitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full; beſides that great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort and refreſhing of heart which followes upon well-doing.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1858:127"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
